Administration Interface

Overview

Administration Model

After installation, a server is administered entirely using a web-based administrator interface which requires Javascript support (see browser requirements below). server administration is very straightforward: log into the administrator interface, make configuration changes, and click Save changes.

The administrator web interface has been divided into the following pages:

Status pages, showing useful, dynamically updated status information
Configuration pages, containing configuration settings for all relevant aspects of the product
Management pages, providing various management functions such as configuration import and export, and product update management

In addition, every administrator interface page shows a summary of status information in the header of the page. This status information includes current service status (service running, license status, etc), remote access and site-to-site connection counts and limits, and currently logged in user. The status overview page, opened when you log in, contains a "dashboard" of all basic status information, updated dynamically (without the need to refresh the page).

Making Configuration Changes

Whenever configuration changes are made, the VPN service is restarted which takes a few seconds and drops existing user and site-to-site VPN connections. A notable exception is changing user authentication settings: changes to user authentication settings has immediate effect but does not disrupt existing VPN connections.

In case you accidentally lose connectivity to the server due to configuration changes, you always have the fallback of using the locally available Firefox browser to fix any configuration problems. The local Firefox browser is automatically started when the server starts up, but it can also be started by double clicking the icon on the desktop.

The server has an internal configuration and status database which acts as a central repository for system related configuration and status information. Any changes you make to the server's system configuration files will only have temporary effect, and will be overwritten by the product next time the VPN service is restarted. Please do not modify system configuration files unless you are certain it is necessary and done correctly.

Browser Requirements

web administration interface requires Javascript support. server can be configured with the local Firefox browser automatically installed on the server, or you can use administration interface from another computer with one of the following supported browsers:

Firefox (1.5 or newer)
Internet Explorer (6.0 or newer)
Safari (2.0 or newer)

A local Firefox browser is started automatically during server start-up. If you want to use another computer, open the browser and enter your server IP address or domain name to your browser address field. Note that remote access to the administration interface can be restricted through configuration.

By default uses a self-signed SSL certificate. This is a common practice, but causes a browser certificate warning whenever an administrator or user connects to the web UI. You can configure to use an external SSL certificate from any commercial certificate provider which removes the certificate warnings; see below for details.

Contents

Header Status Information

Status

Overview
User Connections
Site-to-Site Connections

Configuration

Network
Routing & Firewall
User Accounts
Site-to-Site Connections
License & Maintenance

Management

Reboot
Shut Down
Product Updates
Import Configuration
Export Configuration
Export Diagnostics

Header Status Information

Header status information is shown in top of the administration user interface. Header status information contains the following elements.

Status indicates the current status of the server:

Active

server is running normally. If you are using a demo license, status also indicates remaining demo license time.

Active with errors, Invalid license

server license key is invalid or has been terminated. If you have problems with your server license, please contact support. server cannot be used without a valid license.

Active with errors, Demo license (expired)

Demo license has expired. If you want to continue using you need to buy a server license. server cannot be used without a valid license.

Active with errors, Server(s) not responding

At least one of configured network servers (DNS, WINS, RADIUS, or router) is not available, or at least one site-to-site connection is down. server itself is working normally. To determine the source of the problem, see Status → Overview → Network Status.

Inactive

service is stopped. This is a temporary state.

Starting

service is starting after saving new configuration settings.

Stopping

service is stopping. service restarts when applying new configuration settings.

Internal error, Reboot pending...

An internal error has occurred. server reboots automatically in order to fix the problem. If reboot does not help, you might need to reinstall server, see Server Installation.

Maintenance reboot, Reboot pending...

server is rebooting for maintenance reasons. To adjust maintenance reboot time and date, see License & Maintenance page.

User Connections - The number of active VPN user connections and the maximum number of simultaneous VPN user connections allowed by the server license.

Site-to-Site Connections - The number of active site-to-site connections and the maximum number of simultaneous site-to-site connections allowed by the server license.

Current User - administration interface login username.

Logout - Click link to log off from the administration interface.

Status

Status page provides detailed information of your server's current status:

Overview contains an overview of server status.
User Connections contains detailed information of current and previously active user VPN connections.
Site-to-Site Connections contains detailed information of current and previously active site-to-site connections.

You can also use SNMP to monitor server status. For more information, see SNMP Monitoring. You can download the MIB from the link provided in the Overview status page or directly from downloads.

Overview

The status overview page summarizes server status conveniently in a single page. The overview page is updated dynamically (using Ajax updates), which makes it convenient for diagnosing errors. If the status of a certain field is not yet available, ... (three dots) is shown instead of status text; the field will be updated automatically when the status becomes available.

Service Status contains the following fields:

Status - See Status description from Header Status Information.
User connections - Number of active VPN user connections.
Site-to-site conns - Status of configured site-to-site connections. Status text shows site-to-site username, and the other endpoint IP address if the connection is Up. The arrow between the site-to-site username and the other endpoint IP address indicates the initiator of the connection: a right arrow indicates that this server is the connection initiator, a left arrow indicates that this server is the responder. Status may be either Up or Down.
Service uptime - The time for which service has been continuously running. Saving new configuration and reboot causes service restart and resets the service uptime.
Last maint. reboot - Date and time of the last maintenance reboot.
Next maint. reboot - Date and time of the next maintenance reboot. To adjust maintenance reboot date and time, see License & Maintenance page.
Last update - Date and time of the last product update.
Software version - Current server software version. If there is a product update available, the text (update available) is shown following the version number. To get the product update immediately, see Product Updates page.

Network Status contains the following fields:

Internet - Current address and subnet of the Internet Connection, network device MAC address, total traffic received / send through the network device, and traffic limit (if configured). If dynamic DNS has been configured, also shows the dynamic DNS name and the IP address it currently resolves to (with about 5 minute delay).
Private network - Same information for the private network connection (if configured).
DNS/WINS/RADIUS - Status of configured network servers. Status may be either OK or Not responding.
Routers - Status of routers configured into network settings or routing. Status may be either OK or Not responding.

Hardware Status contains the following fields:

CPU usage - Current processor usage. If the processor usage is continuously near or over 95%, you should consider upgrading the hardware in order to secure performance with heavy VPN usage.
Memory usage - Current memory usage. If the memory usage is continously near 100%, you should consider increasing system memory in order to secure performance with heavy VPN usage.
Virtual memory usage - Current virtual memory usage. When the server runs out of physical memory, it uses virtual memory stored on the hard disk instead. If virtual memory is continuously used, your server performance suffers slightly. The more virtual memory in use, the more performance will drop. Ideally virtual memory is not needed or only needed temporarily.
Uptime - Time since last computer reboot.

License Status contains the following fields:

License key - server license key. Empty when demo license is used.
Name - server license name. If demo license is used, the duration left of the demo license is also shown.
Users - The maximum number of simultaneous user VPN connections allowed by the server license.
Site-to-site - The maximum number of simultaneous site-to-site VPN connections allowed by the server license.
License Server - Indicates whether the server is connected to the license and update management server. Status may be either Connected or Not Connected. If the cannot establish a connection to the license and update management server at least once a week, the server will consider its license to be expired.

Download VPNEASE-MIB.txt link allows you to download MIB file for SNMP monitoring. For more information, see SNMP Monitoring.

User Connections

User connection graph shows the VPN user connection history of the last 7 days. The red horizontal line in the graph shows the maximum number of simultaneous VPN user connections allowed by the server license.

Below the graph is a list of active VPN user connections containing the following columns:

Username - username for the connection.
Connection time - Duration of the VPN connection, and for closed connections (if history is active), the time when the connection was closed.
Notes - Notes may contain one or more of the following messages:

Secondary pre-shared key - Connection was established using secondary pre-shared key.
No NAT-T support - Client operating system does not have NAT-T support (e.g. Windows 2000 without NAT traversal update). This prevents VPN usage from the networks where NAT is used.
Restricted by license - VPN connection was successfully established, but the maximum number of simultaneous VPN user connections was already active. User is not able to use VPN connection.

Details - Click the link to open VPN connection details. See Details for Selected User below.

Details for Selected User contains following fields:

Username - username for the connection.
Connection start time - VPN connection start date and time in server time zone.
Connection end time - VPN connection end date and time in server time zone.
Connection duration - VPN connection duration (if connection closed).
Remote address - Outer IP address of the VPN client. Domain name is shown below the IP address, if domain name can be resolved.
VPN address - VPN IP address of the VPN client. The VPN IP address is reserved for this connection from the VPN client address range, unless a fixed IP has been configured or forced by a RADIUS Framed-IP-Address attribute. For more information about the VPN Client address range, see Network page.
Linux PPP device - Linux PPP device name for this VPN connection. If you wish to inspect information related to the VPN connection using Linux tools (for instance, through an SSH connection), use this device name to identify the connection.
Linux PPP MTU - Maximum transfer unit set to the Linux PPP device. The PPP connection will fragment any IP packets larger than this amount of bytes. The fragmented packets are sent inside the VPN connection as individual packets, ensuring that the encrypted packets visible to the network are not fragmented and do not exceed the configured size. Note that this MTU is intentionally smaller than the MTU configured in Network settings, because the L2TP/IPsec tunnel adds overhead when data is encapsulated into the tunnel.
Total bytes transferred - Total number of bytes transferred during the VPN connection.
Total packets transferred - Total number of packets transferred during the VPN connection.
Current transfer rate - Current incoming and outgoing transfer rates of the VPN connection.
Maximum transfer rate - Highest incoming and outgoing transfer rates during the VPN connection.
Pre-shared key - Pre-shared key used to establish the VPN connection. This can be either Primary or Secondary.
NAT traversal (NAT-T) support - Status can be either Yes or No. Clients without NAT-T support (e.g. Windows 2000 without NAT traversal update) cannot establish a VPN connection from networks where NAT is used, or if the server resides behind a port forwarding firewall.
Connection restricted by license - Status can be either Yes or No. If the connection is restricted, the maximum number of VPN user connections is already active and the user cannot use the VPN connection.

By default only active VPN connections are shown in the status table. Click Show history to also show closed connections, or if history is already active, click Hide history. server keeps track of all connections in the last 30 days across reboots.

Details are not updated automatically on the detailed status pages. You need to click the refresh button of your browser to update connection details.

Site-to-Site Connections

Site-to-site connections status page is similar to the user connections status page described above. Details for selected connection contains additional field Connection mode. This can be either Initiate connection or Respond to a connection depending on site-to-site configuration. For more information about site-to-site configuration, see Site-to-Site Configuration.

Configuration

server configuration settings contains following configuration pages:

Network
Routing & Firewall
User Accounts
Site-to-Site Connections
License & Maintenance

After saving configuration, an Activating Configuration page is shown. Applying new configuration restarts the service, disconnecting all active VPN connections. After service restart, the Status/Overview page is shown.

If you have changed your server IP address, or the server has received a new IP address from a DHCP server, your browser will not be able to reconnect to the server. In this case Activating Configuration page will be displayed indefinitely. Type the new address to your browser address bar and relogin into administration interface to continue.

Each configuration page contains Save changes button. If you leave the configuration page without pressing Save changes button, all configuration modifications are discarded.

Network

The network configuration page provides control over network interfaces, addressing, dynamic DNS, and various other basic networking features.

Network Setup defines the configuration type used with server. In One network interface configuration one network interface is used for both receiving encrypted IPsec packets from the Internet and for sending decrypted plaintext packets to the company private network. In Two network interfaces configuration one network interface is connected to the Internet and the other to the company private network.

Internet Connection contains configuration settings for the Internet connection:

Network interface - Network interface used for Internet connection.
IP address selection - Network interface IP address may be configured automatically (Automatic (DHCP)) or set manually (Set IP address).
Static IP address - Static IP address for the network interface. You may enter an IP address and a subnet mask into the separate Subnet mask field, or enter an address and a mask in the CIDR format to this field (for instance, 10.0.0.1/8 is equivalent to IP address 10.0.0.1 and subnet mask 255.0.0.0). When using the CIDR format, you do not need to enter the subnet mask separately. Available only if Set IP Address is selected.
Subnet mask - Subnet mask for the network interface. If IP address contains subnet mask (CIDR), the value of this field is ignored. Available only if Set IP Address is selected.
Default gateway IP address - Default gateway for the network interface. When using a static IP address, this setting is mandatory. When using DHCP, will use the DHCP-assigned default router automatically, but you may override that setting by defining an IP address here.
MTU - Maximum transfer unit for the network connection. server ensures that encrypted L2TP/IPsec packets containing user data never exceed MTU bytes in size. As a result, the VPN connection never requires packet fragmentation and can be configured to limit packet size to suit even demanding networks. Packets exceeding a certain size will be fragmented, but fragmentation occurs inside the L2TP/IPsec tunneling, and is not visible to the network. The Linux PPP device MTU, which you can see from VPN connection details, is derived from this value by subtracting the amount of overhead imposed by the L2TP/IPsec tunneling. This smaller MTU is the packet size limit for user data packets before they are fragmented inside the VPN connection. The default value for MTU is usually suitable for all networks.
Uplink speed (Mbps) - You may reduce the maximum bandwith available for VPN usage by setting uplink speed. If left empty, no uplink speed limit will be applied. This value is set in megabits (one million bits per second), which is the typical unit for cable and ADSL connections. If you set this value higher than your actual network uplink bandwidth, the setting will be ineffective. You should set this value slightly lower than your actual bandwidth; for instance, if your uplink speed is 2 Mbps, you could set this value to 1.9. Note that many network connections are asymmetric. In particular, ADSL connections are often sold, for instance, as "8/1" which means an 8 Mbps downlink and 1 Mbps uplink. This setting relates to the uplink of your Internet connection.
Client traffic handling - Defines how outgoing remote access and site-to-site VPN traffic is handled (when routing packets from a VPN connection through this network interface):

Use NAT - Network Address Translation (NAT) is applied to the traffic. This means that the source address field of every outgoing packet is changed from the VPN IP address to the address of the server. This simplifies routing, because the recipient sees the traffic as coming from the server instead of the VPN connection. However, with this setting you cannot easily initiate connections towards remote access VPN clients or hosts behind a site-to-site connection; they have to initiate connections instead. This is the default setting.
Use Proxy ARP - Network interface responds to ARP requests targeted to the VPN clients. For more information, see Proxy ARP. This makes it appear as if the VPN clients were directly connected to the network instead of being accessible by routing through the server.
Don't use NAT or Proxy ARP - Neither NAT nor proxy ARP is applied to the traffic. The traffic is routed without changes. This is the most transparent option. Traffic sent back to remote access and site-to-site VPN connections must be "routed through" the server, which requires routing table changes to other network devices. However, this setting makes connections fully bidirectional, i.e., you can also access network services exposed by VPN clients or initiate connections to a remote subnet of a site-to-site connection.

Private Network Connection contains configuration settings for the private network connection. The configuration settings are identical to the Internet Connection.

DNS Servers configuration allows you to configure DNS servers for server manually, or use DNS servers received from DHCP. DHCP option for a network is available only if network connection IP address is received automatically using DHCP. Configuring a working DNS server is mandatory.

Dynamic DNS allows you to use server with changing public IP address. At the moment server supports the following dynamic DNS service providers: DynDNS, DHS International, Open Domain Server, and DyNS. You need to have an account for your dynamic DNS provider in order to configure a dynamic DNS name update. Dynamic DNS configuration has following configuration fields:

Provider - Dynamic DNS provider name. Empty name means that dynamic DNS is not in use.
Username - Your dynamic DNS account username.
Password - Your dynamic DNS account password.
Full hostname - Your dynamic DNS account full hostname. E.g. example-vpn.dyndns.org.
IP address to update - What IP address to update for the dynamic DNS hostname. Use Internet connection IP address means that the address of the Internet connection network interface is used directly (regardless of whether the address is public or private). Use NATted Internet connection IP address means that the address of the Internet connection network interface is used after any NATting has been applied. For public addresses this is the same as the first alternative; this option is useful when private addresses and a NAT is used. obtains the public (NATted) address to be updated from the license server. Finally, Use the following IP address means that a specific manually configured IP address is used.
Static IP address - The IP address to update to the dynamic DNS provider. Only required if Use the following IP address is selected above.

VPN Connection Settings contains configuration settings for VPN clients, consisting of the following fields:

Primary pre-shared key - Pre-shared key used for VPN connections. Either primary, or secondary pre-shared key can be used to establish VPN connection.
Secondary pre-shared key - Pre-shared key used for VPN connection. If secondary pre-shared key has been defined, either primary or secondary pre-shared key can be used to establish VPN connection.
VPN client DNS servers - VPN clients may use either DNS servers defined into DNS Servers configuration above (Use network connection DNS servers), or DNS servers may be defined for VPN clients separately (Set DNS servers).
Primary DNS server IP address - Primary DNS server for VPN clients. Available only if Set DNS servers is selected.
Secondary DNS server IP address - Secondary DNS server for VPN clients. Available only if Set DNS servers is selected.
Primary WINS server IP address - Primary WINS server for VPN clients, optional.
Secondary WINS server IP address - Secondary WINS server for VPN clients, optional.
VPN client subnet - IP address subnet used for VPN client IP addresses. The VPN client address range must be contained inside this subnet. The lowest and two highest addresses of the VPN client subnet are reserved and must not be used for any other purpose.
VPN client address range - IP address range used for VPN client IP addresses. VPN client address range must be in the VPN client subnet. Fixed IP addresses, either manually configured or assigned through RADIUS Framed-IP-Address attribute, must not be inside the client address range (but may be out of VPN client subnet).
VPN client traffic compression - Compression for VPN client traffic. If disabled, the server will reject attempts to enable data compression for VPN connections regardless of VPN client settings. If enabled, server will attempt to enable data compression for VPN connections, but if a VPN client rejects compression it will allow the connection to be negotiated without compression. In essence, when enabled, the VPN client controls whether compression is enabled or not (see Encryption and Standards for a list of compression algorithms supported by different VPN clients). If compression is enabled, it may increase effective throughput of uncompressed data by up to 100%, but increases CPU usage considerably. The default and suggested setting is to enable compression.

With a help of secondary pre-shared key, you can change your pre-shared key without an instant need to deliver the new pre-shared key to all users. You may use both pre-shared keys and delete the old key after you have verified that all users have the new key.

Routing & Firewall

Default Route defines the default route for IP routing. You can select which network to use for default gateway, and you can either use the default gateway configured on Networking page or enter a router IP address manually. If forced routing is enabled (see below), this setting only applies to non-VPN traffic (such as RADIUS, SNMP, SSH, and web traffic).

Additional Routes allows you to define routes in addition to the default route. Typically these are useful when needs to route traffic to multiple subnets comprising a company intranet. The network and router can be selected for each route separately. Routes apply in order of subnet scope: a stricter (smaller) subnet applies with higher priority than a looser (larger) subnet, despite the ordering in the web UI. If forced routing is enabled (see below), the additional routes only apply to non-VPN traffic (such as RADIUS, SNMP, SSH, and web traffic).

Forced Routing. If enabled, allows you to define a default route used for (and only for) remote access and site-to-site VPN traffic. Traffic received from VPN connections is always routed through the router specified. Note that the router specified for forced routing must be from the same subnet as server's own IP address. This setting is only needed in special configurations.

VPN Traffic Firewall Rules contains an ordered list of firewall rules applied to both remote access and site-to-site VPN connections. The rules apply to traffic received from a VPN connection before it is routed onwards. Rules are applied in top-down order, with the first matching rule specifying the action for a data packet being filtered. If no rule matches (or if the firewall rule list is empty), the default rule is to allow traffic. Individual packets can be selected using their destination address, protocol, and port. The VPN traffic firewall is stateful: once an outbound packet has been accepted, response packets for that traffic "flow" are automatically also accepted.

Firewall. If Enable simple firewall (routing through) is enabled (which is the default), causes to act as a simple router with automatic network address translation (NAT) for routed traffic:

In the one interface setup, allows to receive traffic from the Internet connection interface and route the traffic onwards through the same interface. The source address of routed packets is network address translated (NAT) to the address of the Internet connection network interface.
In the two interface setup, allows to receive and route traffic from both the Internet connection and private network connection interfaces. Traffic is routed in all combinations except from Internet to private network (port forwarding can be used instead): Internet → Internet, private network → private network, private network → Internet. The source address of routed packets is network address translated (NAT) to the address of the interface through which the packets are routed (Internet or private network connection).

When configuring firewall rules we suggest you first add a "block all" rule (subnet 0.0.0.0/0, action Deny) as the last rule, and then add exceptions to the list before the "block all" rule.

The VPN Traffic Firewall Rules settings apply to both remote access and site-to-site VPN connections. The firewall rules are applied when traffic is received from a VPN connection and routed onwards to external network hosts. Separate rules for remote access and site-to-site traffic cannot be currently defined.

If you wish to apply different firewall rules for remote access traffic and site-to-site traffic, or wish to apply different firewall rules for individual users or user groups, we suggest you use an external firewall device and use the default configuration (accept all) for your server.

Port Forwarding allows you to define port forwarding rules, which apply to traffic received on the Internet connection interface. Each rule specifies an incoming protocol (TCP or UDP) and a port whose traffic is forwarded to a specified address and port. For instance, you can specify that traffic received for TCP port 80 on the Internet connection is forwarded to port 8080 of a host with the IP address 10.0.0.1. The forwarded connection is routed using routes specified in the default route and additional routes sections. Port forwarding rules are typically only relevant when is used as a simple router (see Firewall above).

User Accounts

This page contains settings for user authentication: you can configure external RADIUS server(s) and/or locally authenticated users. If both are configured, local configuration is checked first, and if the username being authenticated is not locally configured, RADIUS servers are queried next. RADIUS servers are not required, local users can be configured instead.

RADIUS Servers allows you to configure RADIUS servers used for both VPN and web authentication. You can configure either only the primary RADIUS server, or both primary and secondary RADIUS servers. If the primary server fails to respond, the secondary server is tried instead. Each RADIUS server needs the following settings:

(Primary/Secondary) RADIUS server address - IP address of the RADIUS server. A domain name cannot be used for the server.
(Primary/Secondary) RADIUS server port - UDP port of the RADIUS server. Default is 1812, the standard RADIUS port.
(Primary/Secondary) RADIUS shared secret - RADIUS authentication secret in string (ASCII) format. You should configure the same authentication secret to your RADIUS server.

NAS Identifier allows you to define a RADIUS NAS-Identifier attribute for the requests sent by the server, which allows better identification in your RADIUS server.

See Authentication Options for more details about RADIUS authentication possibilities, and how to configure server to be used with Windows Active Directory (AD).

Users allows you to configure users into the local user database for both VPN and web authentication. Use the small plus, minus, up, and down icons to add, remove, and organize users (the order of user entries does not matter, so you can organize the list in any order you wish). The following fields are present for each user:

Username - Username for VPN and web authentication, case sensitive.
Set password - Resets the user password to the value entered here. If no value is entered, the existing password is retained. This allows users to set their own passwords, while an administrator can reset the password if the user forgets his password. If the user has been newly added, an initial password is mandatory.
Fixed IP address - If empty, the user will get a dynamically allocated address from the VPN client address range for each VPN connection. If an IP address is configured here, the user can only have one VPN connection at a time, and the connection will always use this address as the VPN IP address. The fixed IP address cannot be from the VPN client address range, or be any of the reserved addresses (lowest and two highest addresses of the VPN client subnet).
Allow VPNease administration - If set, allows accessing the administrator web interface using this username and password.
Allow VPN access - If set, allows VPN access (default).

Note that all locally configured users always have access to the user web interface.

Site-to-Site Connections

Site-to-Site Connections allows you to configure site-to-site connections. Each connection is either initiated by or responded to by this server (see Site-to-Site Configuration for details). Use the small plus, minus, up, and down icons to add, remove, and organize site-to-site connection entries (the order of entries does not matter, so you can organize the list in any order you wish). Each entry has the following fields:

Username - Username for this site-to-site connection. Must match the setting in the remote server involved in this site-to-site connection.
Password - Password for this site-to-site connection. Must match the setting in the remote server involved in this site-to-site connection.
Remote subnets - A list of IP subnets of the remote network. Traffic destined to addresses inside these subnets will be routed through the site-to-site connection if the connection is available; if the connection is not available, the traffic is blocked. Enter subnets with as a comma separated list, for instance, 10.10.0.0/16, 192.168.10.0/24.
Connection mode - Defines whether this server initiates the site-to-site connection (Initiate connection to a remote server) or responds to a connection (Respond to a connection from a remote server). See Site-to-Site Configuration for details.
Remote server address - IP address or domain name of the remote server. Enter only when connection mode is set to Initiate connection to a remote server.
Remote server pre-shared key - Pre-shared key of the remote server, configured from the Network page of the remote server. Enter only when connection mode is set to Initiate connection to a remote server.

See Site-to-Site Configuration for more information about configuring and troubleshooting site-to-site connections.

License & Maintenance

This page contains various product maintenance settings.

Product License allows you enter a product license key to activate your product subscription. Without a license key the product will use an automatic demo license which will expire automatically. Enter the license key into the License key field. License keys have the form: XXXXX-XXXXX-XXXXX-XXXXX-XXXXX.

Locale Settings allows you to control presentation of timestamps (Timezone) in the web UI, as well as configure the local (Linux) keyboard layout (Keyboard layout). Note that the timezone only affects representation of dates and times in the web UI; the Linux system timezone is always set to GMT so system log entries are also always in GMT. Also note that the keyboard layout setting only affects the Linux graphical desktop keyboard layout and has no visible effect when used remotely.

Product Maintenance controls when maintenance reboots occur (Maintenance reboot weekday and Maintenance reboot time, in timezone configured above) and whether product updates are applied when the product reboots (Check for updates when rebooting). Note that the update check will be done on maintenance reboots but also on any other reboot for any reason. If you disable automatic update checks here, you can still check for and apply product updates manually from the Product Updates page.

Product maintenance reboots are mandatory as they ensure that the system remains functional over long periods of time. avoids disrupting VPN connections when performing a maintenance reboot: when the weekday and time is reached, the product will reboot unless there are active remote access VPN connections. If VPN connections are active, the product will recheck every 24 hours for an opportunity to reboot, but will forcibly reboot severing VPN connections if there is no opportunity within 7 days.

SNMP Monitoring controls (read-only) remote SNMP monitoring of the server. The SNMP read-only access defines the network interfaces through which SNMP should be allowed (Internet and/or private connection, or neither). SNMP community string (password) defines the so-called SNMP community string which authenticates SNMP connections. For read-only monitoring a typical community string is public, which is the default. Note that SNMP access is disabled from all network interfaces in the default configuration.

Remote Management controls remote management access rights. Web administration defines the network interfaces through which the administrator web interface is accessible (the user web interface is always accessible from all network interfaces). SSH connection defines the network interfaces through which SSH access is allowed. Finally, you can set the Linux root password (which is required for remote SSH access) by setting the same password to the Set root password and Re-enter root password fields. If these fields are left empty, the Linux root password is not changed. The default setting after installation is a disabled root password.

SSL Certificate controls server SSL certificate. By default, uses a self-signed SSL certificate, which requires browser users to accept the certificate before proceeding. You can remove these browser warnings by obtaining a proper SSL certificate as follows (the process may vary slightly depending on your certificate provider):

Generate a new 1024-bit RSA key pair and a so called Certificate Signing Request (CSR). The 1024-bit RSA key pair will be used by the server for SSL authentication. The Certificate Signing Request is needed to obtain an SSL certificate from an SSL provider. Save both the private key and the CSR in the PEM format. You can use several different tools to create these files, see e.g. Generating Certificate Signing Requests for OpenSSL instructions.

A correctly generated private key should look something like this:

-----BEGIN RSA PRIVATE KEY-----
...
[several lines of ASCII encoded data]
...
-----END RSA PRIVATE KEY-----

A correctly generated Certificate Signing Request should look something like this:

-----BEGIN CERTIFICATE REQUEST-----
...
[several lines of ASCII encoded data]
...
-----END CERTIFICATE REQUEST-----

NOTE: when you generate the Certificate Signing Request, make sure you set the requested Common Name field to match the intended server domain name. For instance, if the will be accessed by users using the URI http://vpnease.example.com/, set the Common Name to vpnease.example.com. Getting a certificate for an IP address does not work as expected; most browsers will warn about the certificate even if the IP address is correct.
NOTE: please don't use RSA key pairs larger than 1024 bits, as large keys may cause problems with some browsers.

Contact an SSL certificate provider, such as VeriSign or Thawte to get an SSL certificate. The providers typically require you to register and then provide them with a Certificate Signing Request in PEM format. The certificate file you obtain is typically in PEM format and looks something like this:

-----BEGIN CERTIFICATE-----
...
[several lines of ASCII encoded data]
...
-----END CERTIFICATE-----

For a certificate to actually make sense for a browser, you need a certificate for the server (often called the "end entity" certificate), and any intermediate certificates used by the SSL certificate provider. Certificates form a chain from a trusted root certificate (built into your browser) to the end entity certificate; you need the whole chain. Individual certificates in the chain should be separate PEM encoded files (see above). SSL certificate providers often provide a link to required intermediate certificates when they deliver your end entity certificate.
To enable use of an externally generated SSL certificate in a server, paste the PEM file contents into the SSL Certificate Chain (PEM format, server certificate first) and SSL Private Key (PEM format) fields.

The certificate chain field should contain one or more PEM encoded certificates in sequence. The first certificate in the field must be the end entity certificate, followed by any intermediate certificates in a "bottom up" order. The order of the certificates is very important. For instance:

-----BEGIN CERTIFICATE-----
...
[several lines of ASCII encoded data]
...
-----END CERTIFICATE-----
-----BEGIN CERTIFICATE-----
...
[several lines of ASCII encoded data]
...
-----END CERTIFICATE-----

The private key field should contain the RSA private key in a PEM encoded form. For instance:

-----BEGIN RSA PRIVATE KEY-----
...
[several lines of ASCII encoded data]
...
-----END RSA PRIVATE KEY-----

Once you have entered the private key and certificate chain into the user interface, save changes to activate the new certificate. You can test the certificate by connecting to the server from a remote computer using the intended domain name (embedded in the certificate Common Name field). You shouldn't get a certificate warning. You can inspect the certificate chain in most browsers to ensure the chain is correct. If you get unexpected errors, please verify that you filled in the fields as described above. In particular, ensure that the order of certificates in the certificate chain is correct.

Management

server management contains the following pages:

Reboot
Shut Down
Product Updates
Import Configuration
Export Configuration
Export Diagnostics

Reboot

Reboots the server. If automatic updates have been enabled and an update is available, the product update will be applied during the reboot.

Shut Down

Shuts down the server. You should use this feature to shut down the server cleanly, although you can also use normal Linux commands to shut down the server.

Product Updates

Shows a list of product versions, including past versions, the current version, and possibly new version(s). For each version, a short list of features or changes is shown. If a newer version is available, you can force a product update by clicking the Update product (causes reboot) button. Note, however, that product update check requires a reboot, and that the server will be rebooted for a second time after a successful update.

Import Configuration

Import a previously exported configuration file. This feature reboots the server and restores the system to a previous configuration. Note that all existing configuration settings will be lost as a result.

Export Configuration

Export the current configuration data in a single file suitable for backup purposes. The file contains all configuration settings, including pre-shared keys and user passwords, so store the exported configuration file safely. The file does not contain history information, in particular, it does not contain graph history shown in status pages.

Export Diagnostics

Export system information required for diagnostics by support. The exported diagnostics file essentially contains Linux system logs, which allow us to determine the cause of a problem more accurately. The logs do not contains user password or server pre-shared key(s), but may contain other configuration information (such as IP addresses) and usernames.

The diagnostics file is a ZIP file with some product specific metadata and the actual system log files. You can easily inspect the file to ensure that the data is acceptable before you submit the file to support. Note that system log entry timestamps are always in GMT timezone regardless of what timezone is configured from the administrator interface.

Authentication Options

Overview

has a flexible authentication architecture, which can authenticate VPN users against both a built-in local database and remote RADIUS servers. Windows Active Directory can be used through the Internet Authentication Service (IAS) Windows component. Both locally and remotely defined users can be used at the same time. The local database always has priority over any external RADIUS servers. External servers are consulted only if a user is not found in the local database.

User password change feature is not available through the user web interface for RADIUS-authenticated VPN users. Site-to-site connections are always authenticated using the local user database only.

supports a wide variety of different RADIUS servers and proxies. Popular RADIUS servers for small and medium-sized businesses include:

Internet Authentication Service (IAS) for Windows servers
FreeRADIUS, a commercial grade freely available open source RADIUS server

Using Windows Active Directory

Overview

To authenticate users against a Windows server, it is easiest to use Microsoft's Internet Authentication Service (IAS) module available for Windows server platforms. In short, IAS provides a RADIUS server module which authenticates users against Active Directory. IAS is available for Windows Server 2000, Windows Server 2003, and Windows Server 2008 (where IAS is available under the name Network Policy Server, NPS).

Setting up IAS:

Install IAS
Configure each server as a RADIUS client for IAS
Create a RADIUS policy to authenticate and authorize users

There are several ways to control which users are allowed VPN remote access. The detailed instructions below cover the typically desirable configuration where VPN access is granted to users by group membership in a new or existing Windows group (for instance, Users).

Installing and Configuring IAS

These instructions are for Microsoft Windows Server 2003 for Small Business Server, Service Pack 1, but apply to other Windows versions with minor changes.

To set up IAS authentication, do as follows:

Install IAS: Open Start → Control Panel → Add or Remove Programs → Add/Remove Windows Components. Click on Networking Services and click Details.... Check Internet Authentication Service, click OK, and complete the requested installation steps. Reboot after IAS has been installed.
Start IAS: Start → Administrative Tools → Internet Authentication Service.
Add RADIUS clients: click once on RADIUS Clients on the tree view.

Right click to open the context menu, and select New RADIUS Client.
Enter a Friendly name, enter the server's IP address into the Client address (IP or DNS) field, and click Next.
Leave Client Vendor as RADIUS Standard, set Shared secret and Confirm shared secret to the same shared secret configured into the server, and click Finish.

Repeat these steps for all RADIUS clients (i.e., for all servers).
Edit RADIUS policies: click once on Remote Access Policies to see a list of policies.

Right click to open the context menu, and select New Remote Access Policy. Click Next to start the wizard.
Select Set up a custom policy, and enter a useful policy name into the Policy name field (example: VPNease Policy), and click Next.
Click Add... to add a new policy condition, select Windows-Groups attribute, and click Add.... In the Groups window, click Add..., enter the name of the Windows group you wish to indicate remote access (example: Users) to the Enter the object names to select field, click Check Names and OK to close the Select Groups dialog, then click OK to close the Groups dialog. Click Next in the wizard dialog.
Add any other relevant policy conditions here. For instance, you may wish to restrict VPN access to specific servers by identifying them with NAS-Identifier. Note, however, that the syntax used for attribute value matching is regular expression based: "test" will match both "test" and "mytest", while "^test$" will only match "test". See Pattern matching syntax.
Select Grant remote access permission and click Next.
Click Edit Profile... and select the Authentication tab. Change authentication settings so that the following options are enabled: Microsoft Encrypted Authentication version 2 (MS-CHAP v2) and its suboption User can change password after it has expired, Unencrypted authentication (PAP, SPAP). At this point Windows may offer to view a help on authentication; if so, click No. Click Next.
Click Finish. The new policy should now appear in the policy list with highest priority.

If you wish to authorize web administration using RADIUS, see instructions below.
Edit user accounts. Add every allowed VPN user to the Windows group entered above.
To add a fixed IP address for a user (Framed-IP-Address), see below.
Configuration is now completed: restart the IAS server to ensure changes have taken effect. You should test RADIUS authentication with a test client. You can also choose to customize your remote access policy or other settings further.

Limitations

Note that the following features do not interoperate currently with or some VPN clients:

Non-ASCII (international) characters in VPN usernames or passwords
Forced user password change during MSCHAPv2 authentication ("User must change password at next logon" option from Active Directory Users and Computers view)

Configuring Fixed IP Addresses

If you wish to use fixed IP addresses for VPN users, a RADIUS Framed-IP-Address attribute needs to be included in a RADIUS Access-Accept packet. There are two places where RADIUS Framed-IP-Address assignment can be controlled:

IAS remote access policies

Internet Authentication Service (Local) → Remote Access Policies → <policyname> → Properties → Edit Profile → IP → IP address assignment (Framed-IP-Address)

Active Directory user profiles

Active Directory Users and Computers → <user> → Properties → Dial-In → Assign a Static IP Address

When the Active Directory user profile specifies a dial-in address, that address overrides any IAS Framed-IP-Address settings.

There are many ways to configure Framed-IP-Address assignment in IAS; please consult Microsoft documentation for details. However, in simple configurations the following settings are straightforward to configure:

Set the remote access policy IP address assignment (Framed-IP-Address) setting to Server settings determine IP address assignment.
Set the Active Directory user profile Assign a Static IP Address for those users for whom you wish to force a specific VPN address.

Note that this configuration is not sufficient if a user should be forced a different fixed address for different VPN access servers. Please consult Microsoft documentation if you need to configure a more advanced setup.

Configuring Web UI Administrator Authorization

By default users authenticated through IAS are only authorized to use VPN connections and access the user web interface; users are not allowed to login as administrators to the server. Because administrator access is such a critical capability, enabling administrator access for RADIUS authenticated users requires deliberate RADIUS server configuration; see below for RADIUS details.

To enable server web UI administrator access for a IAS authenticated user, do as follows:

Create a new Windows group whose membership indicates that a user should have access to the web UI administrator interface. You may, of course, use an existing group.
Create a new remote access policy (see instructions above), with the following specific settings:

Name the policy clearly, e.g. as VPNease Administrators.
Add policy condition: Service-Type equals Authenticate-Only (used by server for web UI authentication).
Add policy condition: Authentication-Type equals PAP.
Add policy condition: NAS-Identifier matches the set of servers to which administrator access should be granted (you may skip this condition if you don't need server identification).
Add policy condition: Windows-Groups contains a Windows group that you wish to use to signify administrator access (e.g. Administrators).
Add any other policy conditions that you feel are appropriate for ensuring that only administratos are granted access.
Select the action for authenticated users as Grant remote access permission.

Ensure that the policy has a higher priority than a policy for ordinary users.
Open the policy properties and click Edit Profile. Configure the Authentication settings (see above for details). Then select Advanced (Specify additional connection attributes to be returned to the Remote Access server). Click Add..., select Vendor-Specific and click Add.
In the Multivalued Attribute Information window, click Add. Select Enter Vendor Code and enter 26058. Select conformance level Yes, it conforms and click Configure Attribute.... Enter the following values:

Vendor-assigned attribute number: 1
Attribute format: Decimal
Attribute value: 1

Close all the nested windows, and restart the IAS service.

At this point RADIUS requests are first checked against the administrator remote access policy defined above, and if that policy fails to match, the non-administrator remote access policy is then checked. Note that it is important that the administrator policy not reject non-administrator users because web UI authentication for normal users would be prevented. The intent of the policy conditions is to ensure this does not happen.

Finally, note that IAS (or a RADIUS server in general) cannot distinguish between user and administrator RADIUS requests. If the username and password are correct, the server should reply with Access-Accept, and the presence of the vendor specific attribute defines whether the server should allow administrator access. If the attribute is not present, administrator authentication fails despite the RADIUS server returning an Access-Accept response.

More Information about IAS

For more information about IAS:

Internet Authentication Service
Pattern matching syntax
Internet Authentication Service: Frequently Asked Questions
Windows Server 2003 Internet Authentication Service (IAS) Operations Guide

Configuring FreeRADIUS

See wiki.freeradius.org/Configuration.

RADIUS Details

Particular Features of the RADIUS Implementation

RADIUS Service-Type: RADIUS Service-Type attribute is set to Framed-User when authenticating a user VPN connection, and to Authenticate-Only when a user is authenticating to the user web interface. Please ensure that your RADIUS server handles both of these service types correctly (you may deny user web interface access by treating the requests differently, but we recommend that you treat the requests the same way).
RADIUS authentication method: translates the negotiated PPP authentication method (negotiated using PPP inside the L2TP/IPsec encrypted transport connection) directly into RADIUS authentication as follows: PPP PAP (Password Authentication Protocol) is translated to RADIUS PAP, while PPP MSCHAPv2 (Microsoft CHAPv2) is translated to RADIUS MSCHAPv2. Other PPP authentication methods are not supported, because they do not translate well to the RADIUS protocol. In particular, methods other than PAP and MSCHAPv2 would require the RADIUS server to store plaintext versions of user passwords. Web authentication always uses RADIUS PAP authentication.
RADIUS Proxy-State attribute: Access-Request packets sent by contain a Proxy-State attribute because the product contains a built-in RADIUS proxy. This means that all RADIUS proxies in the path from to the RADIUS server, and the RADIUS server itself, must support the Proxy-State attribute to work correctly with server.
RADIUS Framed-IP-Address attribute: respects the Framed-IP-Address RADIUS attribute in an Access-Accept response. The address provided by the RADIUS server is assigned to the VPN client as its PPP address. The Framed-IP-Address must not overlap with the PPP client range configured in the administrator interface.
RADIUS Session-Timeout attribute: respects the Session-Timeout RADIUS attribute in an Access-Accept response.
RADIUS NAS-Identifier attribute: allows you to configure NAS-Identifier which allows you to identify the server reliably even if the server's IP address is dynamic or changes at some point. If NAS Identifier is left empty in the administrator interface, the NAS-Identifier is omitted from RADIUS Access-Request packets.
Username for IAS authentication can be both plain (example: john.doe) or contain a domain name (example: john.doe@example.com). The IAS server accepts both forms. This is not guaranteed of other RADIUS servers.
ignores most response attributes other than message type (Access-Reject, Access-Accept) and MSCHAPv2 related attributes. However, Framed-IP-Address and Session-Timeout are supported.
does not send or receive RADIUS accounting packets.

NAT Compatibility

When a NAT or port forwarding device exists between a RADIUS client ( server) and a RADIUS server, care must be taken to ensure that RADIUS works correctly:

The address of the RADIUS client ( server) as seen by the RADIUS server is the address of the NAT device, which is different from the address of the RADIUS client; a similar difference of apparent address occurs when the RADIUS server is behind a port forwarding device. These differences in apparent address of the other peer affect RADIUS authentication. To ensure that authentication works correctly, configure the address associated with a certain RADIUS secret to the apparent address as seen by the server in question. For instance, if the RADIUS client is behind a NAT device, associate the RADIUS secret in the RADIUS server to the address of the NAT device.
The NAS-IP-Address attribute in RADIUS Access-Request packets may be meaningless and unreliable if a RADIUS client ( server) is behind a NAT device. Use the NAS-Identifier to identify servers instead.

By taking these two basic issues into account, RADIUS should work through NAT and port forwarding devices without any problems.

Attributes of Access-Request Packets

Attributes contained in Access-Request RADIUS packets (VPN authentication, uses RADIUS PAP or RADIUS MSCHAPv2, depending on negotiated PPP authentication method; here RADIUS MSCHAPv2):

Service-Type: Framed-User
Framed-Protocol: PPP
User-Name: varies
MS-CHAP-Challenge: varies (Microsoft vendor specific)
MS-CHAP2-Response: varies (Microsoft vendor specific)
NAS-IP-Address: varies
NAS-Port: 0
Proxy-State: varies
NAS-Port-Type: Virtual
NAS-Identifier: varies (omitted if empty)

Attributes contained in Access-Request RADIUS packets (web authentication, always uses RADIUS PAP):

User-Name: varies
User-Password: varies
Service-Type: Authenticate-Only
NAS-IP-Address: varies
NAS-Port: 0
Proxy-State: varies
NAS-Port-Type: Virtual
NAS-Identifier: varies (omitted if empty)

Supported Attributes of Access-Accept Packets

Attributes supported in Access-Accept packets (for VPN authentication):

Framed-IP-Address
Session-Timeout
VE-User-Administrator-Privileges (VPNease vendor specific)

Authenticating Administrators Using RADIUS

When sends a web authentication request (with Service-Type set to Authentication-Only), you can configure your RADIUS server to grant web UI administrator privileges to the user by adding the following vendor specific attribute to the Access-Accept packet:

Vendor number: 26058
Attribute number: 1 (VE-User-Administrator-Privileges)
Attribute type: Integer
Attribute value: 1

Without this attribute, the user has no administrator privileges and cannot log in through the web administrator interface.

You can download a RADIUS dictionary file with this attribute from the download page.

RADIUS Packet Dumps

The following slightly simplified packet dumps are provided to help resolve RADIUS server configuration problems.

Example packet dumps for RADIUS MSCHAPv2 authentication of a remote access VPN connection against a Windows Server 2003 IAS server:

Frame 1 (N bytes on wire, N bytes captured)
    [...]
Ethernet II, Src: ss:ss:ss:ss:ss:ss, Dst: dd:dd:dd:dd:dd:dd
    [...]
Internet Protocol, Src: x.x.x.x (x.x.x.x), Dst: y.y.y.y (y.y.y.y)
    [...]
User Datagram Protocol, Src Port: XXXX (XXXX), Dst Port: radius (1812)
    [...]
Radius Protocol
    Code: Access-Request (1)
    Packet identifier: 0xXX (X)
    Length: N
    Authenticator: XXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXX
    Attribute Value Pairs
        AVP: l=N  t=Service-Type(6): Framed-User(2)
            Service-Type: Framed-User (2)
        AVP: l=N  t=Framed-Protocol(7): PPP(1)
            Framed-Protocol: PPP (1)
        AVP: l=N  t=User-Name(1): xxxxxxxx
            User-Name: xxxxxxxx
        AVP: l=N  t=Vendor-Specific(26) v=Microsoft(311)
            VSA: l=N t=MS-CHAP-Challenge(11): XXXXXXXX...
                MS-CHAP-Challenge: XXXXXXXX...
        AVP: l=N  t=Vendor-Specific(26) v=Microsoft(311)
            VSA: l=N t=MS-CHAP2-Response(25): XXXXXXXX...
                MS-CHAP2-Response: XXXXXXXX...
        AVP: l=N  t=NAS-IP-Address(4): x.x.x.x
            NAS-IP-Address: x.x.x.x (x.x.x.x)
        AVP: l=N  t=NAS-Port(5): 0
            NAS-Port: 0
        AVP: l=N  t=Proxy-State(33): XXXX
            Proxy-State: XXXX
        AVP: l=N  t=NAS-Port-Type(61): Virtual(5)
            NAS-Port-Type: Virtual (5)
        AVP: l=N  t=NAS-Identifier(32): xxxxxxxx   [omitted if empty]
            NAS-Identifier: xxxxxxxx

Example packet dumps for RADIUS PAP authentication of a user web interface connection against a Windows Server 2003 IAS server:

Frame 1 (N bytes on wire, N bytes captured)
    [...]
Ethernet II, Src: ss:ss:ss:ss:ss:ss, Dst: dd:dd:dd:dd:dd:dd
    [...]
Internet Protocol, Src: x.x.x.x (x.x.x.x), Dst: y.y.y.y (y.y.y.y)
    [...]
User Datagram Protocol, Src Port: XXXX (XXXX), Dst Port: radius (1812)
    [...]
Radius Protocol
    Code: Access-Request (1)
    Packet identifier: 0xXX (X)
    Length: N
    Authenticator: XXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXX
    Attribute Value Pairs
        AVP: l=N  t=User-Name(1): xxxxxxxx
            User-Name: xxxxxxxx
        AVP: l=N  t=User-Password(2): Encrypted
            User-Password: XXXXXXXX...
        AVP: l=N  t=Service-Type(6): Authenticate-Only(8)
            Service-Type: Authenticate-Only (8)
        AVP: l=N  t=NAS-IP-Address(4): x.x.x.x
            NAS-IP-Address: x.x.x.x (x.x.x.x)
        AVP: l=N  t=NAS-Port(5): 0
            NAS-Port: 0
        AVP: l=N  t=Proxy-State(33): XXXX
            Proxy-State: XXXX
        AVP: l=N  t=NAS-Port-Type(61): Virtual(5)
            NAS-Port-Type: Virtual (5)
        AVP: l=N  t=NAS-Identifier(32): xxxxxxxx   [omitted if empty]
            NAS-Identifier: xxxxxxxx

Client Configuration

uses the built-in VPN client provided by your operating system, so no client installation is required. Configuring the built-in VPN client is easy: for Windows 2000, XP, and Vista, provides an automatic VPN connection configuration feature; for other operating systems provides easy step-by-step configuration instructions.

To configure you client for VPN use:

Start a web browser and type in the address of the server into the browser address bar.
Login using the username and password. Note that the same username and password are used for both web user interface and VPN access.
For Windows 2000, XP, and Vista, follow the instructions for automatic configuration.
For other operating systems, select the client operating system from the navigation menu on the left and follow configuration instructions.

You can preview the client configuration interface and optionally test compatibility with an actual client by using our test server. For more information about the test server, see Test Servers.

For some platforms, such as Linux-based systems, additional software is required. Such platforms do not typically have a built-in remote access VPN client, so additional software is mandatory.

Multi-Customer Configuration

Overview

When deploying into operator premises, it is often desirable to terminate VPN connections from multiple customers in the same server, but forward unencrypted traffic to different destinations for each customer.

This scenario is common with operator software and equipment. For VPNs, the following basic issues need to be addresses:

VPN connections must be associated with a specific customer during authentication (e.g. using a name suffix, such as test.user@company1.com).
VPN traffic for each customer must be routable separately (with separate routing rules).
If traffic is forwarded into customer premises (e.g. using a site-to-site connection), overlapping address spaces of customer networks must be dealt with. In particular, a certain address, such as 10.0.0.1, is routed to a different network depending on which customer's VPN connection is sending the packet.
Clients must be isolated from one another, so that customers cannot route packets to other customers' clients.

addresses these issues in the following manner. servers are configured with RADIUS authentication, and the RADIUS Framed-IP-Address attribute is used to assign addresses to VPN connections, with VPN connections from different customers getting VPN addresses from different subnets. Decrypted VPN traffic is routed to an operator router, which can use source routing (routing based on source address rather than destination address) to route the traffic to customer networks and/or servers without problems caused by destination address overlapping.

This solution is described below with detailed configuration instructions. Finally, guidelines for testing a deployed solution are given.

Configuration

Detailed instructions for configuring servers into a multiple customer (shared server) model are given below.

RADIUS Authentication

servers are configured to use RADIUS authentication. Both primary and secondary RADIUS servers should be configured to maximize availability.

RADIUS usernames of the form username@company (e.g. test.user@company1.com) should be used; however, any RADIUS username convention which links a username uniquely to a customer can be used.

The Framed-IP-Address RADIUS attribute is used to assign VPN addresses to all VPN connections. The VPN address assigned is based on a pool of customer specific addresses. The easiest solution is to assign each VPN user of each customer a specific address.

Example: *@company1.com VPN addresses are assigned from 10.0.0.0/24, and *@company2.com VPN addresses assigned from 10.0.1.0/24. By looking at a specific IP address (e.g. 10.0.1.7) the customer can be identified in a router.

Routing

supports multiple alternative methods for handling decrypted VPN traffic: direct, proxy ARP, and NAT. In this solution either the direct or proxy ARP handling should be used, because the VPN address assigned through RADIUS must not be changed or masked (by NAT).

Further, to centralize control over routing, server should be configured to use so-called forced routing. When forced routing is enabled, traffic from VPN connections is routed to a specified router, bypassing the normal routing table entirely. Routing control can then be applied fully in the specified router.

Forced routing is enabled from the administrator interface, page Routing & Firewall → Forced Routing.

Note that remote access users are prevented from sending traffic to one another; any such packets are dropped when forced routing is enabled, unless the external router routes the packets back to the server.

Operator Router

Forced routing target is a router device containing the actual routing tables. This device must be capable of routing traffic based on the source address of incoming packets, so that it can differentiate between packets from different customers. In particular, the destination address of individual packets does not define routing uniquely

Firewall rules of the router must be configured carefully. In particular, the routing rules must ensure that traffic from a certain VPN client address can only be forwarded to the corresponding customer network and vice versa.

A stateful firewall is preferred, but a stateless can also be configured for this purpose.

Other Issues

It is possible to arrange inbound connections to VPN clients in this scenario, i.e. allow hosts from a customer network to initiate connections to a VPN client. If this is desired, firewall rules in the operator router must prevent packets from going to VPN addresses of other customers.

Testing

Because this configuration is relatively complex, at least the following tests should be performed after deployment to minimize the risk of incorrect configuration:

Check that the RADIUS server(s) correctly assign Framed-IP-Address attributes to authenticated users. If assigned addresses are incorrect, security may be compromised.
Check that the operator router receives packets correctly from the when a client is connected.
Check that the operator router correctly forwards packets to each customer, based on the VPN client address (subnet). In particular, test that overlapping destination addresses in a customer network are handled correctly. For instance, if two customer networks contain the private address 10.0.0.1, check that ping packets to the address from two different clients with usernames from the two customer domains are routed correctly, each to its own customer network.
Check that return packets from the customer network reach the VPN client correctly. This can be easily tested by pinging a host in a customer network.
Check that a VPN client cannot reach other customer networks. Also check that hosts in a certain customer network cannot route packets to VPN clients of another customer (i.e., incorrect VPN address subnet).

Quick Installation Guide

Overview

Quick installation requires the following:

A dedicated PC with at least 1 GHz CPU, 256 MB RAM, and 2 GB hard disk
A client computer with a supported operating system (e.g. Windows XP/Vista, Mac OS X)
45 minutes for installation and testing

For comprehensive installation instructions, see Server Installation.

Step 1: Download and Burn Installation CD

Download the latest server ISO image and burn it to a CD or DVD. Please ensure that you burn the ISO image as is instead of creating a data CD containing the ISO image as a file.

Step 2: Check Server Requirements and Install

The server is installed on a dedicated PC with the following minimum requirements: 1 GHz CPU, 256 MB RAM, and 2 GB hard disk. For details, see Server Requirements.

Boot from the server installation CD (you may need to change your BIOS boot settings for this), click Install product, select a hard disk for installation, and confirm installation. The installation process takes about 15 minutes. Once installation is complete, click Reboot computer to reboot, and remove the CD from the drive when it is ejected.

If you are familiar with VMware, you can also install server into a VMware guest. See Virtualization Products for details, and other supported virtualization platforms.

Step 3: Perform Initial Server Configuration

We suggest the following network configuration: the server is installed into the company intranet, to the same subnet where company servers reside. The company firewall is then configured to port forward connections from the company Internet connection to the server to allow VPN access from the Internet (see step 4 below).

Boot the server (you may need to change your BIOS boot settings for this). Login to the administrator interface and perform the following minimum configuration steps:

Go to the Network page.
Check the Internet Connection settings: you should either select DHCP or static address configuration. For static configuration you need to enter a static IP address, subnet mask, and default gateway, and enter a DNS server address manually to the DNS Servers group.
Select a pre-shared key used for computer authentication and enter it into the VPN Connection Settings → Primary pre-shared key field.
Click Save changes.
Go to the User Accounts page.
Add a VPN user by clicking on the plus sign in the Users group. Enter a username and a password for the user.
Click Save changes.

The server status page shows all basic server information. The product will automatically request a demo license for 30 days, and the available demo license time is shown. Check the IP address of the Internet connection and write it down for later use.

Step 4: Configure Company Firewall

Write down the company firewall's Internet IP address, as it is needed for VPN client use. Add port forwarding rules to the firewall, to forward the following protocols and ports from the Internet connection to the server's IP address:

UDP port 500 (IPsec)
UDP port 4500 (IPsec)
TCP port 80 (web UI, optional but recommended)
TCP port 443 (web UI, optional but recommended)

Not forwarding TCP ports 80 and 443 disables access to the web user interface from the Internet. You can access the web user interface from the intranet instead. If you use client autoconfiguration from the intranet, edit the VPN connection properties afterwards, changing the server address from the intranet address to the Internet address.

Step 5: Configure and Test Client Computer

Select a laptop or desktop computer for testing the VPN connection. Connect the laptop to the Internet (not the intranet), open a browser window and enter the IP address of the firewall's Internet connection. Login to the web user interface with the VPN user's username and password (configured in step 3).

Configuring and testing the VPN connection depends on the client computer operating system:

Windows XP and Vista: click Autoconfigure, run the downloaded executable, and reboot the computer. After reboot, open Network Connections, double click on the VPN icon, enter username and password, and click Connect.
Mac OS X: select Mac OS X from the menu on the left and follow configuration instructions.

You should now have a VPN connection and access to all your company resources through the VPN connection.

Note that if you want to test the VPN connection from the intranet for some reason, you need to use the server rather than the firewall's address in the web browser and the VPN profile. Port forwarding does not always work when connections are initiated from the intranet.

Server BIOS Setup

Overview

The PC BIOS controls many aspects of PC hardware relevant to use, such as computer startup procedure and low level hardware configuration. BIOS settings are specific to each motherboard, so the configuration procedure varies widely between BIOS versions.

server does not require any specific BIOS settings. The BIOS setup steps described below are recommended in order to minimize problems during the product installation and usage.

BIOS Setup Steps

We recommend the following BIOS setup steps.

BIOS Update

Check your BIOS version and install a BIOS update if available from your motherboard manufacturer. BIOS updates can prevent problems with operating system hardware drivers, and are especially important for recently introduced motherboard models.

BIOS Configuration

Enter BIOS configuration by booting your computer and pressing your BIOS specific settings activation key (typically DEL, F2, F8, or ESC)
Reset BIOS settings to default values
Configure processor, bus, memory, and performance settings. Use conservative settings (labeled Normal or similar) unless you have a good reason for doing otherwise
Configure boot order

Enable booting from the CD/DVD drive
Enable booting from USB HDD (for USB stick installation)
Enable booting from hard disk
Select boot order as follows: CD/DVD first, USB HDD second, and HDD last

Disable any automatic power management features

These include features such as screen savers, timed shutdown, etc
Such features are not desired in server systems as they may cause unpredictable operating system interactions and service disruptions

Disable extra devices

Disable any extra integrated audio, video capture, wireless LAN, or other unnecessary motherboard-specific devices
Integrated video (VGA) and integrated network interface cards (NICs) should be left enabled as appropriate

Disable anti-virus features (anti-virus detection and warning)
Set BIOS date and time

Note that will update its time automatically, but setting BIOS date and time is still recommended, as it minimizes system discrepancies (e.g. in log files)
Set BIOS time to UTC (Coordinated Universal Time), not your local time zone

Other settings

Enable Quick POST (Power On Self Test) if available; this speeds up the boot-up sequence

Save settings and exit BIOS setup

If any of your BIOS settings is out of the ordinary, write down any special settings for later use. This will help reconfigure the system should BIOS settings be lost due to motherboard NVRAM battery problems.

BIOS in Virtualization Products

Most virtualization products, such as VMware and Virtual PC, also have BIOS settings for the virtual machine hardware. Setting hardware and power management features is not crucial for such environments, as the defaults are usually acceptable for server use. However, boot order must still be configured correctly.

Server Clustering

Overview

To support high throughput and high availability installations, supports a multi-server installation where load is balanced across multiple servers, and failed servers are not allocated any client traffic.

The load balancing and high availability solution is very straightforward: you install multiple servers, and configure a DNS server to map a certain domain name, such as vpn.example.com, to the addresses of the servers. The DNS server then returns a random permutation of the server addresses in response to a client query (performed when the client attempts to establish a VPN connection), effectively sharing load randomly across servers. Further, the DNS server actively monitors each of the servers and removes them from the DNS mapping if they are no longer responsive.

This DNS-based high availability configuration does not require any special version of server, but the servers involved in a "cluster" should be configured in a certain way which we'll discuss in this document. Furthermore, it is preferable that the DNS server be able to monitor and update the DNS mappings dynamically. Although you can use any DNS server which provides a monitoring feature for the installation, we provide an Ubuntu-based VMware appliance which provides a monitoring DNS server based on the Bind DNS server. The VMware appliance is provided free of charge provided that you use it in conjunction with a server installation.

Installation Steps

To install a high availability configuration, do as follows:

Install two or more servers. Note that each server needs a separate product license, and that each product license should have VPN connection limit equal to the total number of potential users. Otherwise product license may restrict connections when one or more of the servers fail.
Configure the servers normally. Because servers are used interchangeably, user authentication should be done using the same RADIUS server(s) in all servers. Client address ranges should not overlap, unless NAT is used for client traffic. Pre-shared key must be the same for all servers.
Test each server separately using a test client.
Delegate a certain subdomain from your main domain for VPN connections. For instance, if you own the domain example.com, you could delegate the subdomain vpn.example.com for high availability VPN connections. Delegation requires changes in your existing DNS servers, in particular, new NS records.
Install two (or more) DNS servers for handling requests to the delegated subdomain. We suggest that you use the Monitoring DNS Server, but any DNS server capable of active monitoring and updates is acceptable.
Configure each DNS server identically, to monitor servers and map suitable domain names to server clusters. You can define multiple server clusters, e.g. customer1.vpn.example.com could map to two servers dedicated for one customer while customer2.vpn.example.com could map to three servers dedicated to another customer. You can also map the root of the delegated subdomain, e.g. vpn.example.com to a server cluster if there is a "primary" server cluster. Make sure that the DNS servers return short Time-To-Live (TTL) values, preferably 60 seconds, for all entries related to server clusters. This allows failover to work quickly and makes load balancing more effective.
Test DNS resolution behavior manually both from the corporate intranet, and from the external network. Check DNS server reaction to an off-line server by turning off one from each server cluster, and checking that DNS mappings change accordingly with an acceptable delay.

How Reliable is Server Clustering?

The overall reliability of the high availability configuration is based on full replication of all servers critical to establishing a VPN connection: DNS servers, servers, and RADIUS servers. A failure of all but one server of each kind is non-fatal for VPN connectivity. This gives you a very high level of availability.

Further, each server is relatively independent, allowing servers to reside in different geographic locations and use separate Internet providers for connectivity. This allows, for instance, you to increase reliability by:

Placing monitoring DNS servers in separate locations and separate Internet connections (you can host them on virtual servers if necessary).
Placing servers behind different Internet service providers to minimize chance of simultaneous network disruption. You can also place the servers in separate IP networks to minimize reliance on Ethernet switches and other supporting devices.
Placing the RADIUS servers in separate locations and separate Internet connections. RADIUS servers can be placed in the Internet although this is not recommended due to the low security level of the RADIUS protocol. Instead, you can place the RADIUS servers in different parts of your company intranet.

Finally, you can minimize the impact of software failures by deploying each server with a different version of the server software (software diversity). This complicates management slightly but minimizes the chance of simultaneous software failure or simultaneously discovered fatal software weakness in all servers.

Overall reliability is dependent on measures at all levels of the enterprise, including electricity and UPS arrangements, cabling and Ethernet switches, Internet connectivity, and the actual servers involved in VPN connections. high availability configuration addresses the reliability of the actual servers, but you need to ensure the high availability of lower level critical resources to maximize overall availability.

Site-to-Site Connections and Clustering

Server clustering can only be used for site-to-site connections with limitations. These limitations stem from the fact the multiple available routes for IP subnets requires the use of active routing protocols (such as RIP and OSPF) for route failovers to work. This complicates network design and implementation considerably.

However, you can configure the following useful site-to-site high availability scenario without using routing protocols:

Deploy the responding side of a site-to-site connection as a server cluster. This is typically a desirable solution because "headquarters" should terminate site-to-site connections from remote sites (a star topology). The headquarters site is thus more critical for site-to-site connectivity and benefits the most from clustering.
Configure each server comprising the server cluster to use NAT for VPN traffic. This is necessary because otherwise the IP subnets of the remote sites would be reachable through multiple routers from an IP routing standpoint, requiring the use of routing protocols. With NAT this IP routing problem is not encountered. However, failover, while allowing new connections to be formed, drops existing connections tied to the NAT address of the failed server. Further, this configuration restricts connectivity between sites so that connections can only be initiated from remote sites. This is typically not a problem, because "headquarters" typically hosts any services needed by the remote sites.
Do not deploy site-to-site initiators with clustering, and configure them normally. Use the server cluster domain name (mapped to all active servers) as the remote endpoint address.

Monitoring DNS Server

monitoring DNS server is a VMware appliance containing a DNS server suitable for server clustering. The server is based on Ubuntu 6.06 LTS with required packages (such as the "bind" DNS server) preinstalled. The appliance contains a monitoring daemon which monitors servers using ICMP Echo Request packets (pings), and reconfigures and restarts the "bind" DNS server according to the status of the servers. The monitoring daemon is configured using a simple XML file specific to the monitoring daemon.

Two DNS servers are required in the high availability configuration. Without high availability of the DNS service, high availability of the would be meaningless. The servers must be installed and configured separately, but the servers must have the same XML configuration file to avoid inconsistent DNS information. The VMware appliance does not automatically synchronize configuration between the two servers.

To install a monitoring DNS server, do as follows (these steps must be done twice to install two servers):

Determine basic DNS and networking information:

The name of the domain delegated to these servers (e.g. vpn.example.com); the delegation must be configured to the DNS servers above this domain (e.g. example.com DNS servers).
The IP addresses of the two DNS servers (which we will call ns1 and ns2).
The IP address of the host for which any mail for the delegated domain should be delivered; this will be used for the delegated domain's MX record, and is mandatory.
The IP addresses of servers participating in server clustering. If you have multiple server clusters (i.e., logical servers comprising multiple servers), you need IP addresses of servers for each cluster, and need to select a name for each cluster. The name will be used for naming subdomains (e.g. cluster1.vpn.example.com).
Note that you may have one (but only one) "unnamed" cluster. This cluster will use the name of the delegated domain (e.g. vpn.example.com) directly. Other clusters must have a name (e.g. cluster1.vpn.example.com). The "unnamed" cluster is convenient when there is a primary group of VPN users.

We will use the following example values below:

Delegated domain name: vpn.example.com
Name server addresses: ns1=172.16.0.1, ns2=172.16.0.2
Mail delivery address: mail=10.0.0.1
Clusters: cluster1=[192.168.0.1, 192.168.0.2], cluster2=[192.168.1.1, 192.168.1.2, 192.168.1.3]
NB: actual IP addresses would not typically be private addresses like these. Private addresses can be used for both DNS servers and servers if company firewall is configured with port forwarding.

Unpack the appliance (ZIP file; contact support to get the appliance), and rename the unpacked directory to something suitable (e.g. vpn-example-com-ns1). Start VMware, open the virtual machine, and review virtual machine configuration settings. Start the virtual machine.
Login as root. The root password is always "changeme" in the appliance. Once logged in, change the password immediately.
Open the monitoring DNS server XML configuration file, named /etc/vpnease-dns-server.xml. Edit the configuration settings to match the networking information described above. The configuration file has detailed configuration instructions in XML comments.
Restart the monitoring server by executing:

$ /etc/init.d/vpnease-dns-server restart

Test that the configured clusters respond appropriately:

$ dig @127.0.0.1 cluster1.vpn.example.com
...

$ dig @127.0.0.1 cluster2.vpn.example.com
...

The output should contain A records for all currently responding servers belonging to the cluster. If you repeat the request, the list of server addresses should change in a "round robin" manner.
You should check that the DNS server reacts appropriately to a failed server by turning off a server, and checking that the DNS resolution step (above) returns updated results within a minute or two.
Halt the virtual machine (using the "halt" command), review virtual machine settings, ensuring especially that the virtual machine will automatically start when the host is rebooted. Turn on the virtual machine and ensure that it starts correctly without assistance. (If possible, reboot the host and ensure that the virtual machine starts correctly without assistance in this case too.)
Repeat these steps for the second name server. It is preferable to copy the configuration XML file using e.g. the "scp" command instead of typing the configuration in twice.
Turn off and make backups of the virtual machines by compressing the virtual machine directories using e.g. ZIP.

Server Installation

Overview

server installation requires a dedicated PC. You can also install server using a virtualization product, which allows you to share the hardware with other software.

To install the server to a dedicated PC:

Read and accept the legal documents.
Download Live CD ISO image and burn it to a CD or a DVD.
Boot the computer from Live CD.
Live CD user interface opens automatically. Select Install Server and follow the instructions.
Reboot the computer to start the server.
Log in to administrator interface, modify the configuration settings according your network setup, and add user accounts.
Configure client computers and verify VPN connection functionality.

Installing server on a virtualization product contains the same steps except the following:

You must create a virtual machine for the server.
There is no need to burn the Live CD ISO image to a CD. You can configure the ISO image to be used as a medium for a virtual CD/DVD drive instead.
If you are using VMware, you can also use a prepackaged virtual appliance and bypass the Live CD installation steps. After unpacking and taking the appliance into use, you can start configuring the server directly.

See Virtualization Products for a list of supported virtualization products.

Prerequisites

General

Check the following prerequisites before starting installation:

You must read and accept the License Agreement and Privacy Policy before you are allowed to use the product (even for demo use).
Download server ISO image or prepackaged VMware appliance (if using VMware) from Download page.
Check Server Requirements for hardware and network requirements. If you are going to install server on a virtualization product, see Virtualization Products.
Check computer BIOS settings. For more information, see Server BIOS Setup.

Network Parameters

You'll need the following information about your network configuration:

Internet settings (if connecting server to the Internet):

IP address settings: DHCP, or static IP address, subnet mask, and default router.
If you have a dynamic IP address, check your dynamic DNS provider settings (recommended). See FAQ for more information.

Internal network settings:

DHCP, or static IP address and subnet mask for internal network
Additional routes within the internal network, if applicable

If you have multiple company sites, you will need individual subnet and address information for every site to set up site-to-site connections.

Network Configurations

has two basic network configuration models: one and two network interface configuration.

In one network interface configuration the network interface is used both receiving encrypted IPsec packets from the Internet, and for sending decrypted plaintext packets to the company private network. This model is preferred because of its simplicity and is suited to configurations, where the company firewall port forwards the ports required by from the Internet to the server residing in the internal network.

In two network interface configuration one network interface is connected to the Internet and the other to the company private network. This model is suited to following configurations:

server is used as a firewall
server is deployed in conjunction with an existing firewall
No port forwarding is desired
The company network is relatively large or complex

In addition to these two basic models, provides several smaller options to make the product fit in the best possible manner to your company network:

NAT for user traffic (Configuration → Network). When enabled, performs an address translation (NAT) on decrypted VPN traffic. This simplifies routing by making all user traffic seem to come to the company network from the address of the server. This setting is preferred for most network setups and is the default choice.
Proxy ARP for user traffic (Configuration → Network). In normal routing your company hosts and/or routers are configured to route all traffic destined to clients and remote site-to-site networks through the server. Proxy ARP makes the respond to ARP queries for VPN addresses (and other routable addresses) on the local network, making it appear as if clients resided directly in the network which the is connected to. This allows you to use VPN client addresses which are a part of the local IP subnet.
Basic firewall and routing functions (Configuration → Routing & Firewall). allows you to route non-client traffic through (in which case NAT is applied to the traffic), configure port forwarding entries, and prevent access to certain company servers from VPN users. With Source Routing option all VPN traffic can be routed to a particular router with a full routing table, such as the company firewall.

Step 1: Installing server with Live CD

server installation is done with Live CD. To start the Live CD, do the following:

Start the computer and insert the Live CD into the CD/DVD drive. The Live CD should start automatically. If not, adjust your BIOS settings to prefer booting from CD/DVD over other media. Alternatively, you may be able to choose a different boot device for one particular boot, depending on your BIOS features.
In the Live CD start menu you have the following options:

Install in safe graphics mode (default) - starts the Live CD in safe graphics mode. Safe graphics mode uses computer BIOS provided video mode, which minimizes display compatibility problems.
Install in native graphics mode - starts the Live CD in native graphics mode. Native graphics mode uses a hardware specific driver. Use this option if the Live CD start fails with the default option.
Check CD for defects - checks Live CD for possible transfer errors.
Memory test - runs a memory test.

Select Install and press Enter to start the Live CD.

The Live CD will open the Live CD user interface automatically. server is managed using a local or a remote web browser. For installation and initial configuration a local browser is used because network settings have not yet been entered. To install server do the following:

Select Install / Recovery from the Live CD user interface.
Read through the License Agreement and Privacy Policy and check the related checkbox (assuring that you have read and accepted the documents). Click Next.
The installer will show you possible installation target media found on the computer. If the installation medium (e.g. a USB stick) is not yet connected, connect it now and click Rescan. You can also choose to attempt recovery of configurations from an existing installation, by checking the Attempt recovery check box. Select one of the target media and click Next.

If you are using USB stick as an installation medium, the USB stick is re-partitioned and formatted in a customized manner for the product. If you want to uninstall server later, the Live CD allows you re-partition and re-format the USB stick after which you can use the stick normally to exchange files.

Details of the selected medium are shown. If recovery was attempted, recovery information availability is also shown. Make sure that this is the correct target for installation. Installation will erase all existing data on the medium. If satisfied, click Start installation.
The installer will re-partition and format the target medium and install software on the medium. The duration of this step is dependent on the performance of the target medium, but typically takes 5-30 minutes. Installation on a USB stick is typically slower than on a normal hard disk.
When installation is complete, click Reboot computer. Remove the Live CD after the CD has been ejected from the CD drive.

The server starts the administrator interface automatically after reboot. If server startup fails, see the FAQ.

Step 2: Configuring Server

After installation and rebooting, server administrator interface is started automatically. Minimum configuration steps for setting up the server are:

Go to the Configuration → License & Maintenance. If you want to test the product with a demo license, leave License key empty. If you have a license, type the key to the License key field. Select the valid timezone and keyboard layout. Check Product Maintenance and Remote management settings. Note that automatic product updates are disabled by default, enable them if you desire automatic product update (check) on reboot. Save changes.
Go to the Configuration → Network and select either one or two interface network setup. Check the interface and IP address information of the network(s). Go down to the VPN Connection Settings. Set the pre-shared key for IPsec authentication. Write the pre-shared key down temporarily for later use when configuring client(s). Check that VPN client subnet and VPN client address range don't overlap with existing subnets and address ranges used inside the company intranet. If they do, choose another subnet and address range for VPN clients. Save changes.
Go to the Configuration → User Accounts and give username and password for each user. Alternatively, configure RADIUS authentication (see Authentication Options for details). Save changes when you're done.

Users can change their passwords from the user web interface. A administrator does not have access to users' passwords. If a user does not remember his password, administrator can set a new password for the user.

Depending on your network setup, you may require additional configuration steps before server is ready for use. See Administration Interface for more detailed information about server configuration possibilities.

After configuring the server, you should test the VPN connection from the Internet by configuring one VPN client computer. To set up a client, you (and all users) will need the following information:

(or company firewall) domain name or IP address
username and password
server pre-shared key

See Client Configuration for more information.

Step 3: Configure External Devices

If you have chosen to use port forwarding to access the server from the Internet, you need to configure port forwarding rules to your firewall. See Server Requirements for a list of required ports and protocols.

Check that IP routing configuration of other network devices (especially firewalls and routers in your corporate intranet) have been configured correctly. In particular, if you are using site-to-site connections, please check Site-to-Site Configuration for routing requirements.

Step 4: Finalizing Installation

If you selected not to use automatic updates, plan an upgrade check for every month or so. It is important to upgrade the product if upgrades become available.

If you installed to a normal IDE/SCSI hard disk, you should plan when the hard disk is replaced. Typical hard disk lifetimes are 3-5 years. If you installed to a flash RAM (USB stick or Compact Flash hard disk), no maintenance is typically required for the installation medium.

Server Requirements

Server Hardware Requirements

Processor: 32-bit or 64-bit x86, recommended 2 GHz or more
Memory: minimum 256 MiB
Networking: one or two 10 Mbps or faster Ethernet network interfaces (NICs) depending on the network configuration
Storage: 2 GB or larger, dedicated storage device for installation. Storage device can be either hard drive (USB, IDE, SCSI, Serial ATA) or flash memory (USB stick, IDE Compact Flash)
BIOS: if USB stick installation is used, must be capable of booting from a USB HDD. If installation target is smaller than 4 GB, requires a BIOS capable of booting from hard disks larger than 512 MB.

Server Hardware Compatibility

server is based on the Ubuntu Linux distribution, with up-to-date hardware compatibility for all standard PC hardware. The latest is based on Ubuntu 6.06 LTS (Dapper Drake). For more information on hardware compatibility issues, see:

Ubuntu's support pages
Ubuntu's hardware support Wiki
Documentation for Ubuntu 6.06 LTS (Dapper Drake)

Although is based on the Ubuntu distribution, it is not supported by Ubuntu. Contact support or your service provider in all support matters. Please do not contact Ubuntu for support.

A few practical tips in choosing hardware:

Select recent but not the newest possible hardware to minimize risks with immature hardware
Use well-known, quality storage devices with long guarantee periods (3 years or more)
Flash-based storage devices can be considerably slower than magnetic storage devices, but have no moving parts and can provide more reliable long term operation
Favor low temperature and/or fanless components over more powerful, fan-cooled components
Check Linux (Ubuntu) compatibility from your seller
If Linux compatibility is uncertain, consider using a virtualization product as a platform for the product. This eliminates compatibility issues and allows you to choose any host operating system (e.g. Windows or other Linux variant)

Network Requirements

Internet connection speed: minimum 512 kbps.
Internet Service Provider (ISP) must not block the following protocols and ports:

UDP/500 (IPsec)
UDP/4500 (IPsec)

The following protocols and ports are optional for usage:

TCP/80 (HTTP, administrator and user web user interface access)
TCP/443 (HTTPS, administrator and user web user interface access)
IP protocol 50 (IPsec ESP without NAT traversal, required for clients without NAT traversal support)

Software Requirements

server has a web-based administrator interface, which requires Javascript support. server can be configured with the local Firefox browser automatically installed on the server. To use the administrator interface from another computer the following browsers are supported:

Firefox (1.5 or newer)
Internet Explorer (6.0 or newer)
Safari (2.0.1 or newer)

also has a separate web-based interface for VPN users, which provides user account management and guides for configuring the VPN client for supported operating systems. user web interface does not require Javascript and works with almost any browser, such as:

Firefox (1.5 or newer)
Internet Explorer (5.0 or newer)
Safari
Opera
Konqueror
W3m

Virtualization Products

In addition to using dedicated hardware, server can also be installed on existing hardware by using a virtualization product, such as VMware, Microsoft Virtual PC, Microsoft Virtual Server, Microsoft Hyper-V, KVM (free), or Parallels. See Virtualization Products for more details.

Installation on top of a virtualization product is recommended if:

There is existing server hardware that can comfortably share some capacity for terminating remote access connections. Typically only about 10% of server capacity is required to run a remote access gateway, yielding great hardware savings. If your company manages customer equipment, this is a great opportunity for providing additional options to your customer with minimal investment.
Your hardware is not compatible with the Linux distribution (Ubuntu) which is used as a basis for the product. Virtualization can overcome hardware compatibility issues, because any host operating system (e.g. Windows or other Linux variant) can be installed on the host hardware. will only see standardized virtual hardware.
Your networking hardware is not Ethernet based (e.g. PPPoE or a modem connection). The virtualization product will hide the actual networking hardware and present a virtual Ethernet device for .
You plan to install multiple remote access servers with different configurations, or you need some supporting servers and wish to minimize hardware costs.

has been tested with all major virtualization products. See Virtualization Products for more detailed information.

High Reliability Installations

For the high reliability installations we recommend one of the following:

Use a virtualization product and configure RAID hardware to the host computer. This provides storage reliability for the server as well.
Use a reliable USB stick (flash memory) or Compact Flash IDE (SATA) hard disk instead of a normal (magnetic) hard disk. Hard disks are a common cause of failure in server systems, and flash-memory-based hard disks avoid this common cause.

does not support RAID devices directly. To use software or hardware RAID, use a virtualization product and configure RAID in the host computer.

PC Hardware Reliability Tips

Minimize the number of cooling fans and invest in quality fans. Cooling fans are a common source of failure. A failing fan results in an increased computer temperature leading to increased risk of processor and other chip instability, increased risk of expansion card failures, and decreased lifetime of hard disks.
Check temperature. Allow the system to run for a day or two, and check case temperature. You can typically check the temperature values by restarting the computer and entering the BIOS setup screen. BIOSes typically display temperature and fan information in one of their information screens. Refer to your computer hardware manuals for information about expected operating temperatures.
Use quality components. Purchase quality components (motherboard, memory, network card). Low quality components may lead to failures which are difficult to trace and correct.
Run a "torture test". Run torture tests on your hardware to ensure the hardware performs correctly under heavy load. Common hardware torture tests include: Memtest86 (included on the Live CD), Prime95, Super PI, SiSoftware Sandra, and BOINC.
Replace hard disks before they fail. If you use a normal magnetic hard disk, replace it with a new one before it fails. Typical lifetime of a hard disk in normal use is 3-5 years. Check your hard disk data sheet for mean-time-to-failure (MTTF) estimates.

Site-to-Site Configuration

Overview

A site-to-site VPN connection routes traffic between two company sites by encrypting and sending traffic using an IPsec-protected "tunnel". In practice, a site-to-site connection acts like an ordinary router: IP packets destined to a remote site are routed to the server configured with the site-to-site connection, and are then transparently routed through the Internet to the other company site.

The configuration steps for a site-to-site connection are as follows (we cover these steps in detail below):

Determine network configuration
Determine server addresses
Configure site-to-site responder endpoint
Configure site-to-site initiator endpoint
Make routing changes to your other devices
Verify the site-to-site connection
Verify site-to-site routing

Setting up site-to-site VPN connections involves many devices: the servers, firewalls, routers, and intranet computers at each site. Typical problems in configuring site-to-site connections are routing and firewall related, so follow the configuration steps carefully. Incorrect routing typically results in lack of end-to-end connectivity even though the site-to-site VPN connection itself is working correctly.

Configuration Steps

Determine Network Configuration

Design your desired network configuration beforehand. In particular, you need to determine which IP subnets are used in the site-to-site endpoints. This information is required to configure IP routing correctly, so that each site-to-site connection endpoint knows which packets to send over the site-to-site VPN connection.

Determine Server Addresses

Determine whether servers have a public or a private address (port forwarding) and if either address is dynamic and requires dynamic DNS configuration. This information is required to decide which endpoint will initiate a connection, while the other endpoint will only respond to connections.

A site-to-site VPN connection is always initiated by one peer while the other peer is a passive responder. This has no impact on the actual site-to-site connection: the connection is fully symmetric regardless of the direction in which the connection is initiated.

A peer can act as an initiator if the responding peer is reachable by the initiating peer. This is usually the case if: (1) the responding peer has a public IP address, or (2) the responding peer has a private IP address but port forwarding has been configured. In some cases operator firewalls may prevent incoming connections to the responding peer even when the peer has a public IP address. If the responding peer has a dynamic address, configure dynamic DNS for the peer and use the dynamic DNS address when configuring the initiator. Note that the initiating peer may itself be behind a NAT device or be otherwise unreachable from the Internet. Even in such cases the formed site-to-site connection is fully symmetric.

If neither peer can act as an initiator, the site-to-site connection cannot be configured. If both peers can act as an initiator, it doesn't matter which one is configured as the initiator.

Configure Site-to-Site Responder Endpoint

Configure the responding server first, defining a username and a password for this site-to-site connection. The IP subnets of the initiating end need to be defined for the responding endpoint so that traffic can be routed correctly. If the responding server has a dynamic (but public) IP address, you should configure dynamic DNS updating.

Check that your product license allows site-to-site connections.

Configure Site-to-Site Initiator Endpoint

Configure the initiating server, using the same username and password as configured into the responding endpoint. The pre-shared key of the responding endpoint also needs to be defined, you can find this pre-shared key from the network configuration page of the responding server; the pre-shared key is the same one used for normal VPN users. The IP subnets of the responding end need to be defined for the initiating endpoint so that traffic can be routed correctly.

Check that your product license allows site-to-site connections.

Make Routing Changes to Your Other Devices

Because the IP topology has changed, some routing changes are usually needed. In short, you need to ensure that packets sent by computers in the initiating server's network to the responding server's network are routed to the initiating server and vice versa. If this is not the case, the site-to-site connection will be formed but connections will fail silently because of incorrect routing.

Verify the Site-to-Site Connection

Ensure that both endpoints report the site-to-site connection as being up in their status overview page. If not, check site-to-site username, password, and pre-shared key settings in both endpoints. Also check that addresses have been entered correctly and your firewall does not prevent the connection from being formed.

Verify Site-to-Site Routing

Ensure that packets are routed correctly between IP subnets of each endpoint. For instance, you may use the 'ping' command to check connectivity between pairs of computers. This is a critical step because routing configuration issues are the typical cause of site-to-site connectivity problems.

Troubleshooting

Troubleshooting site-to-site connectivity issues can be time consuming because failures are often silent in nature: the site-to-site connection appears to be up, but connectivity nevertheless fails for some reason.

The quickest approach is to check settings first, and then employ a network traffic analyzer, such as the free Wireshark tool (formerly known as Ethereal) to quickly isolate the problem. More detailed troubleshooting instructions are given below.

Site-to-Site Connection Does Not Come Up

This problem is typically relatively easy to diagnose and fix. First, review the configuration steps above. In particular, ensure that the site-to-site connection username, password, and pre-shared key have been entered correctly. Remember that the initiating peer uses the pre-shared key configured in the responding peer's network configuration page.

If all settings look correct, something is preventing the IPsec protocol from establishing a secure connection between the two sites. Check the following:

Check that your firewall is not blocking IPsec traffic, in particular UDP ports 500 and 4500 must be allowed (these are used by the Internet Key Exchange protocol, a part of IPsec standard).
Some Internet operators block or treat IPsec packets in incompatible ways. Please check with your operator that they do not prevent IPsec connections at either end.
If you use NAT and/or port forwarding for connections, check that the NAT and port forwarding settings are correct. Note that if port forwarding is used, the port forwarded site must be configured as the responding peer, otherwise the site-to-site connection cannot be formed.

Note that it may take a few minutes for a site-to-site connection to be established. The initiating peer will retry a site-to-site connection roughly every two minutes. To speed up the process, configure the responding side first, and the initiating side afterwards. This ensures that the first site-to-site connection attempt is successful.

Site-to-Site Connection Comes Up But Connectivity Fails

This is the most common problem when configuring site-to-site connections: the site-to-site connection itself is shown to be up in the web interface, but traffic still cannot be sent between the sites. The cause is very often incorrectly configured routing.

Check the following:

Ensure that you have correctly identified the IP subnets at each site, and that the subnets have been correctly configured into each site-to-site endpoint. Remember that you need to enter the IP subnets of the responding site to the initiating side's configuration, and vice versa.
For each site, ensure that routes for other devices (other than servers) are configured correctly. You need to ensure that packets sent from one site to the IP subnets of the other site are routed to the local server. How this is done depends on your network configuration.
Check the firewall and access control settings on the source and destination computers, ensuring that they allow communication with IP addresses involved in the attempted connection. Sometimes servers may be configured with access control allowing connections only from the local IP subnet. In this case connections from the remote site may be rejected, unless the NAT option is used in the local server.
If you receive ICMP "time to live exceeded" packets in response to e.g. ping (ICMP echo) packets, a routing loop is most likely causing connectivity problems. The routing loop may be caused by incorrect subnet specifications in site-to-site configurations. In particular, one site-to-site connection endpoint routes a packet to a remote endpoint, but the remote endpoint does not actually provide routing for that subnet, and sends the packet back through the same or another site-to-site connection, possibly resulting in a routing loop. If this is the case, recheck subnet definitions for site-to-site connections at each end of every site-to-site connection.
Check that your product license allows site-to-site connections at each site-to-site endpoint.

If you cannot resolve the problem using the instructions above, please follow the detailed instructions on how to "retrace" the site-to-site connection data flow below. We recommend that you use a network traffic analyzer, such as Wireshark to make diagnosis as quick as possible.

Retracing Site-to-Site Connection Data Flow

In case you cannot resolve the problem by the suggestions above, you can diagnose the problem further by "retracing" the data flow. To do this, decide which test connection you will use for testing first; you may use ping (ICMP Echo Request) or a HTTP web server connection, for instance. Regardless, a network connection is attempted by a computer (computer A) at one site (site A) to a computer (computer B) at another site (site B). A connection initiation packet is routed from site A to site B (through the site-to-site connection) and a response packet is routed back from site B to site A.

To diagnose a site-to-site connection problem in detail, we need to determine which part of the round trip between computers A and B fails first, as follows:

Computer A to server at site A:

The IP packet sent by computer A with destination address set to computer B should be routed to server at site A. If the site-to-site connection is up, you can verify this step quite reliably by looking at the detailed status of the site-to-site connection in question, and ensuring that the transfer (TX) counter increases for the site-to-site connection with every connection attempt. If so, it is quite likely that IP packets are routed from computer A to the server. Note that counters are updated with a delay of about one minute.
In the simplest case the server is used as the default gateway and this step should be automatically OK.
If a separate default gateway is used, that gateway should have routing configured so that every subnet of the responding site is configured with the server as the gateway.
If computer A should send packets intended for remote sites directly to the server, each computer (such as computer A) in the site needs to be configured with appropriate routes. This network configuration is not recommended because it requires many route configurations and is thus error prone.

server at site A to server at site B:

The IP packet with source address set to computer A and destination address set to computer B should be routed from one server to the other. If the site-to-site connection is up, this is the case if the site-to-site connection has correct routing configuration. You can verify this step by verifying that as the transfer (TX) counter of the server at site A increases, the corresponding receive (RX) counter of the server at site B also increases. Note that counters are updated with a delay of about one minute.

server at site B to computer B:

This step typically works because computer B typically has an address reachable from the server at site B. However, there are two complications. First, the source address of the IP packet may either be computer A (if the NAT option is not used) or at site B (if the NAT option is used). Second, computer B may have a firewall blocking access from whichever source address is present in the IP packet.

Computer B to server at site B:

This is similar to routing a packet from computer A to the server at site A. However, if the NAT option is used in the server at site B, the destination address of this response IP packet is the address of the server at site B, sometimes simplifying routing.

server at site B to server at site A:

This is similar to routing a packet from the server at site A to the server at site B. You can verify this step by ensuring that the transfer (TX) counter of the server at site B increases, and that the receive (RX) counter of the server site A also increases. Note that counters are updated with a delay of about one minute.

server at site A to computer A:

This step typically works because computer A typically has an address reachable from the server at site A. However, check that an intervening firewall or a built-in firewall of computer A is not blocking the response.

Using a network traffic analyzer, such as the free Wireshark tool (formerly known as Ethereal) is recommended as it makes it much quicker to isolate the problem.

Virtualization Products

Overview

What Is Virtualization?

Virtualization products allow sharing the resources of one physical computer with multiple virtual machines. Each virtual machine resembles a physical computer but consumes only a fraction of the physical computer's resources. The resources used by the virtual machine are provided by the host computer. Virtualization allows you to run multiple different products and operating systems on the same hardware. For instance, the host computer may run Windows Server 2003 while virtual machines (also known as guests) may run Linux, Windows XP, and other operating systems, without any compatibility issues.

With virtualization, you can even overcome differences between processor architectures. For instance, can be installed on PowerPC-based Mac OS X computers, even though itself requires an Intel/AMD x86 processor.

supports all major virtualization products. You can install on an existing server computer by first installing a supported virtualization product and then installing into a virtual machine. This saves money and resources, and further hides the host hardware from , allowing you to use hardware and network configurations not directly supported by .

Supported Virtualization Products

supports the following virtualization products:

VMware Server
VMware ESX Server
VMware Workstation
Microsoft Virtual Server
Microsoft Virtual PC
Microsoft Hyper-V
KVM (free)
Parallels Workstation
Parallels Desktop

Other Virtualization Products

should work correctly in all full virtualization systems, which provide virtual PC hardware (32-bit x86 processor) to the virtual machine. Such systems include Qemu and Xen in full virtualization mode. However, does not support installation into these alternative systems, and functionality cannot be guaranteed.

Installing Using Virtualization Products

Common Requirements

Virtual hard disk of at least 2 GB (about 1.86 GiB)
256 MiB of memory for virtual machine (512 MiB recommended)
One or two virtual network interfaces (Ethernet)

Installing server on virtualization products is very similar to installing onto physical hardware. There are product specific variations on how virtual machines are created, started, and configured for server use (automatic starting on host startup, and so on). Please refer to your virtualization product manuals for more information. Instructions for VMware Server and KVM are described below as illustrations. Also see Common Post-Installation Steps below.

A prepackaged virtual appliance is available for VMware on the Download page. No product installation is necessary when using a virtual appliance: simply unpack the appliance files, review virtual machine configuration, and take the virtual machine into use.

Common Post-Installation Steps

After configuring the server, you should perform the following steps to ensure that the product performs as reliably and securely as possible.

Virtual machine boot order: Check that the virtual machine starts into when the virtual machine is rebooted. In particular, check that there is no virtual CD/DVD image in the virtual machine CD/DVD drive. Alternatively, change virtual machine boot order to prefer booting from hard disk instead of CD/DVD.
Virtual machine autostart on host reboot: If available in the virtualization product, ensure that the virtual machine starts automatically when the host reboots. This is important for instance with power outages, to ensure that remote access service is automatically restarted after the host computer reboot.
Take a backup or a snapshot of the virtual machine: Power off the virtual machine and take a backup of the virtual machine directory. Some virtualization products also provide a snapshot capability, which can be used instead. A backup or a snapshot allows you to roll back to an earlier configuration in case of a problem with the product (a configuration error, accidental deletion of user accounts, etc).
Host computer automatic reboot: Because most operating systems have trouble performing reliably over extended periods (months), it is recommended to set up an automatic reboot schedule for the host computer. For instance, the host computer could be configured to reboot once a week or once a month. This minimizes risk of host computer related remote access service disruptions. will automatically reboot the virtual machine periodically to minimize disruptions caused by the virtual machine.
Host computer network configuration: The host computer should not have a configured IP address in order to minimize risks of host computer intrusion. If the host computer needs to have an IP address (which is quite typical), host computer firewall settings should be carefully configured and the remote access should be reachable only through a firewall port forwarding function.
Host computer power management: Check host computer BIOS and operating system power management settings. The host computer should never power off, despite lack of any activity.
Host computer screensaver: Check host computer screensaver settings. The preferred screensaver is a simple black screen to minimize performance impact of the screensaver.
Host computer RAID settings: If your host computer uses RAID disk array, check that RAID settings are correct. In particular, check that the host computer alarms you somehow if integrity of the RAID configuration is threatened by a failing disk.
Host computer UPS settings: If your host computer is connected to a UPS, check that the UPS settings are correct. Check that UPS alarms are delivered to you using e.g. email, and simulate a power failure to ensure that the alarms are actually delivered.

Known Limitations

Virtual machines running should not be suspended. Suspend/resume causes a large time synchronization discrepancy which disrupts VPN service. Please shut down virtual machines instead of suspending them.

VMware (Workstation, Server, ESX Server)

VMware has several different virtualization products intended to a wide range of users; from desktop to data center use. They also provide free products, such as VMware Server and VMware Player. works best with VMware Server and VMware ESX Server. can be used with other VMware products as well, but they may be less ideal environments. For instance, VMware Workstation does not provide an easy and reliable way to start virtual machines automatically when the host computer boots up, which is important for a network service like .

To install using VMware Server, do as follows (these steps are for Linux version of VMware Server, but are very similar to the Windows version; ESX Server installation is slightly different but the same parameters apply):

Create virtual machine

Select File -> New -> Virtual Machine. Click Next.
Select Custom. Click Next.
Select Guest Operating System value 2. Linux, and select Ubuntu from the Version dropdown menu. Click Next.
Select an appropriate name for the virtual machine (e.g. Server), and check the storage location for virtual machine files. Click Next.
Select number of processors as One. supports multiprocessor environments, but in typical cases the extra performance is not necessary. Click Next.
In some VMware products you will be asked whether the new virtual machine should be made private (visible only to VMware user creating the virtual machine) or not. Select whichever is more appropriate for you. Click Next.
Specify memory size of 512 MB (recommended). 256 MB is the minimum supported by . Click Next.
Select Network Connection value Use bridged networking. This connects your virtual machine directly to the local Ethernet network. Click Next.
Select I/O Adapter Types value SCSI adapter / LSI Logic. In general the default selection is best. Click Next.
Select Create a new virtual disk. Click Next.
Select Virtual Disk Type value SCSI (Recommended). Click Next.
Specify size for new virtual disk as 2.0 (GB). Check the Allocate all disk space now and Split disk into 2GB files checkboxes. Click Next.
Select a name for the virtual disk file. The default is typically OK. Click Finish.
VMware will now create the virtual disk file, which should take about one minute. When complete, VMware will return you to the main administration window.

Finalize configuration and configure bootup from Live CD

Open virtual machine settings window by clicking Edit virtual machine settings.
Select Options tab.

Select Power and check the Power on after opening the virtual machine and Close after powering off or suspending checkboxes.
Select Snapshot and check the Disable snapshots checkbox.
Select Startup/Shutdown, select the Power on virtual machine under the label On host startup, and Shut down guest operating system under the label On host shutdown.

Select Hardware tab.

Select CD-ROM 1 (IDE 1:0) (or similar). Check the Connect at power on checkbox. Select the Use ISO image: option, and click the file browsing icon to locate the Live CD ISO image file.
Select Floppy 1 (or similar), and click Remove to remove the unnecessary floppy device.
Select Ethernet 1 (or similar). Ensure that Connect at power on checkbox is checked, and that the Bridged: Connected directly to to the physical network option is selected.
If you wish to use a configuration with two network interfaces (see Server Requirements), click Add.... Select Ethernet Adapter from the Hardware Types list and click Next. Select Bridged: Connected directly to the physical network option for Network Connection, ensure that the Connect at power on checkbox is checked, and click Finish.

Click OK to close the Virtual Machine Settings window.

Boot from Live CD and install server

Start the new virtual machine by clicking the green "play" icon (Power On).
Enter the BIOS setup menu of the virtual machine: get virtual machine focus by clicking on the virtual machine display area, and press F2 when instructed by the BIOS. The BIOS menu should appear.
Navigate to the Boot menu by pressing the right arrow key multiple times. Navigate the list of boot devices using the down arrow key until the CD-ROM Drive text is active. Press the plus key (on the keypad) until the CD-ROM Drive is first in the boot list.
Navigate to the Exit menu by pressing the right arrow key. Ensure that Exit Saving Changes is selected and press Enter. Confirm the save operation by selecting Yes and press Enter.
The Live CD should now boot in the virtual machine. The remaining installation steps are the same as in a normal installation. Select the virtual hard disk as the installation target. Remember to eject the CD-ROM or disable the CD drive of the virtual machine before initial configuration, so that boots correctly from the hard disk after installation. For more information, see Server Installation.

Finalize installation

Disable boot from the Live CD as follows. In the main VMware screen click Edit virtual machine settings. Select CD-ROM (IDE 1:0) (or similar), and clear the Connect at power on checkbox. Close the settings window by clicking OK.
Check the Common Post-Installation Steps above.

KVM

KVM (Kernel-based Virtual Machine) is a free, high quality virtualization technology built directly into modern Linux platforms. KVM provides high performance through hardware assisted virtualization. It thus requires a relatively modern PC with either Intel VT-x or AMD-V (also known as AMD Pacifica) processor virtualization technology for maximum performance. We suggest that you use a reliable and stable Linux distribution for deploying KVM. For instance, the Ubuntu Server is a good free platform for this purpose.

KVM management is command line based, which allows ordinary Linux scripts to be used for e.g. startup. An alternative solution is to use some GUI wrappers for KVM such as virt-manager. The following instructions assume that the host has X server configured. Installation without X server is similar, except that remote VNC connections are used throughout the installation.

To install on KVM, do as follows:

Login with proper permissions (e.g. as root). Read the KVM manual pages for an overview of KVM and its options.

$ man kvm
$ man kvm-qemu   # may vary depending on distribution

Create a virtual machine

Create a directory for the virtual machine:

$ mkdir /<path>/kvm/vpnease
$ cd /<path>/kvm/vpnease

Create a virtual disk for the virtual machine:

# in the virtual machine directory
$ dd if=/dev/zero of=disk.bin bs=1M count=4096  # 4 GiB

VPNease installation

If necessary in your distribution, start KVM kernel modules:

$ modprobe kvm        # for both AMD and Intel
$ modprobe kvm-amd    # for AMD
$ modprobe kvm-intel  # for Intel

Start the installer:

$ kvm -hda disk.bin \
      -cdrom vpnease_<version>.iso \
      -boot d \
      -std-vga \
      -net nic,vlan=0,model=rtl8139 \
      -net tap,vlan=0,ifname=vpnease0

You should configure network connectivity for the virtual machine at this point. The virtual machine will have a virtual eth0 Ethernet device, which will send and receive packets from the host vpnease0 (or whatever name was given above) TAP device.

The simplest approach is to configure a static address from a virtual subnet for the virtual machine, and assign the host TAP device an address from the same virtual subnet. Then, allow routing with NAT (MASQUERADE or SNAT) from the TAP device to the external network. Finally, add port forwarding for UDP ports 500 and 4500 (IPsec) and TCP ports 80 and 443 (web UI) from the external network to the virtual machine.
Several other configurations are possible. For instance, KVM supports a bridged connection mode. See KVM documentation for more information on network configuration alternatives. Note that the KVM "user" networking mode is not recommended because of its limitations.

Install normally, see Server Installation. Once installation is complete, power off the virtual machine.
To perform initial configuration, start KVM again with the following options (the difference to the previous options is that booting happens from the hard disk rather than the CD drive):

$ kvm -hda disk.bin \
      -boot c \
      -std-vga \
      -net nic,vlan=0,model=rtl8139 \
      -net tap,vlan=0,ifname=vpnease0

When initial configuration is done, ensure that the virtual machine gets a demo license. This indicates that networking functions at the basic level. You can also test client connections at this point. Once done, shutdown the product from the web UI and exit KVM.

Configure automatic startup for the server:

The KVM command line above is suitable for starting up the KVM virtual machine from e.g. /etc/rcN.d/ startup scripts, except that a different graphics device needs to be used. The following command line starts up the KVM virtual machine as above, but with VNC graphics suitable for startup from system scripts even without X being installed on the host (you can change the VNC display number to whatever you wish to use):

$ kvm -hda disk.bin \
      -boot c \
      -std-vga \
      -vnc :1 \
      -net nic,vlan=0,model=rtl8139 \
      -net tap,vlan=0,ifname=vpnease0

You should place a startup script in your system startup (consult your Linux distribution for specifics), which (1) probes the KVM kernel modules if necessary (see above); (2) starts up the KVM virtual machine e.g. as above; and (3) sets up the host networking correctly for the virtual machine. For the last step, you can use KVM interface scripts, or simply write your custom scripts.

Test your setup

Reboot the host computer.
Once the system is up and running, launch a VNC viewer to connect to the virtual machine graphics display:

# this varies per distribution
$ vncviewer :1.0
$ tightvncviewer :1.0
$ xvncviewer :1.0
$ xtightvncviewer :1.0

If everything has been set up correctly, you will see the web UI. Ensure that server gets an IP address, and that connection to the license server is up: this indicates that networking functions correctly.

QEMU is a virtualization platform almost identical to KVM, but it does not require hardware virtualization support (Intel VT-x or AMD Pacifica). However, it is considerably slower and thus not recommended.